<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mirrour to confesse well for such persons as doe frequent this sacrament / abridged out of sundry confessionals, by a certaine deuout and religious man.</title>
            <author>Heigham, John, fl. 1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 158 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S5316</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">39960805</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 39960805</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150416</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150416)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1949:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mirrour to confesse well for such persons as doe frequent this sacrament / abridged out of sundry confessionals, by a certaine deuout and religious man.</title>
                  <author>Heigham, John, fl. 1639.</author>
                  <author>Charles Borromeo, Saint, 1538-1584.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>309 [i.e. 310], 1 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Iohn Heigham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[St. Omer?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item contains five of the six parts mentioned in STC (2nd ed.) The Psalter of Jesus is lacking.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹², F-R¹².</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 310 numbered 309; signatures A₃, and A₅ marked E₃ and E₅ respectively.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>A mirrour to confesse well -- Certaine very pious and godly considerations / by Iohn Heigham -- Divers devout considerations / by Iohn Heigham -- Certaine advertisements teaching men how to lead a Christian life / by S. Charles Boromeus -- A briefe and profitable execise of the seaven principall effusions of the pretious blood of our Lord Iesus Christ / translated ... by Iohn Heigham.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Catholic authors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:1"/>
                  <p>A MIRROVR TO CONFESSE WELL FOR SVCH PERSONS as doe frequent this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abridged out of ſundry Confeſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, by a certaine deuout, and Religious man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>FOR IOHN HEIGHAM, ANNO 1624.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150416:2"/>
                  <head>A MIRROVR TO CONFESSE WELL, For the vſe of ſuch as doe frequent this Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>HAving made the ſigne of the CROSSE, thou shalt ſay the <hi>Confiteor,</hi> if thou canſt, and afterwards thou shalt ſaie:</p>
                  <p>Father, I was confeſſed in ſuch a time, and did my Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance inioyned me: and now accuſe my ſelfe, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150416:3"/> not come to Confeſsion with that preparation and ſorrowe for my ſinnes as I ought.</p>
                  <p>I haue not loued, nor than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked God for his benefites, as I was bound.</p>
                  <p>I haue made my prayers, and heard Maſſe, with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted minde.</p>
                  <p>I haue receaued my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our with ſmale deuotion: of al which I doe confeſſe my fault.</p>
                  <p>I haue bene diſobedient, and made thoſe that were at home with me to contende, and haue contended alſo my ſelfe. It is a Veniall Sinne.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150416:3"/>
                  <p>I haue had manie idle and vaine thoughts, they are V. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue had euill thoughts, but againſt my will, and haue caſt them off, as much as lay in me: yet I do accuſe my ſelfe of negligence in this behalfe.</p>
                  <p>I haue had euill thoughts, and willingly haue delighted my ſelfe in them, and would haue put them in execution, if I had could. Here thou muſt explicate, what thoughts they were, and the number of them alſo, becauſe they be Mortal ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>I haue willingly thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150416:4"/> of others, and iudged rashlie of them in grieuous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that without any lawfull cauſe. It is a M.S. but in things of no moment, or of verie ſmale, it but a V. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue ſuſpected euill of others, without any certaine opinion, it is a V. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue doubted in matters of fayth. If vnwillingly, it is a V. S. If with deliberation, it is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue giuen credite to dreames, enchantments, and other ſuperſtitions, but not ſtedfaſtly. If ſtedfaſtly, thou
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150416:4"/> muſt tell what, and how it was: as alſo if thou haſt made, or cauſed to be made, any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, or witchcraft: &amp; if thou haſt borne about thee any ſuperſtitious writings, of what ſorte they were.</p>
                  <p>I haue thought, that in ſome thinges God doth not well, but this agaynſt my will. It is a V. S. if willinglie, it is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue in my heart, deſired euill to ſome perſons, but not with intention that any euill should happen vnto them. It is a V. S. but if it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re with a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150416:5"/> full purpoſe, and in weightie matters, or of importance, as to wish their death, &amp; the like: it is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>Then hath a man a ful pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, when he doth marke the euill, and yet doth wish it to any one.</p>
                  <p>I haue bene ſorrowfull at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens good, &amp; taken joye in their euils that were of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, and this with a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mind. It is a M. S. but if it were without deliberation, it is a V. S as alſo in light mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150416:5"/>
                  <p>I haue taken pleaſure in my Mortall ſinnes of time paſte, and haue bene ſory that I had not committed more and this with a ſtedfaſt minde, It is a M.S. as alſo to deſire that one ſinne mortally, or forſake not mortall ſinne.</p>
                  <p>To prayſe one for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting a mortall ſinne, or to exhorte him to doe it, is a M. Sinne.</p>
                  <p>I haue made a vowe, &amp; haue not kept the ſame able. It is a M. S. Thou muſt tell what vowe it was, becauſe not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150416:6"/> to keepe a vowe in a ſmal matter, as of a <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> is no M. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue lyed, without ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or hurte of my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, it is a V. S. with an oath it is alwaies M. S. although it were in ſport. So likewiſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doeſt ſweare that which is doubtfull for true, &amp; when thou haſt no minde to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which thou dooſt promiſe with an oath: &amp; when thou dooſt ſweare to doe any thing that is a mortall ſinne, if indeed thou haue a minde to fulfill it, there be two mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150416:6"/> ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>It is a M. S. not to fullfill an oath made of a good thing, if thou be able to keepe the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe it is a M. S. to make any other ſweare falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if thou doeſt thinke that thou doeſt ſweare falſly.</p>
                  <p>To ſweare that thou wilt do any thing, which thou dooſt either know or ſuppoſe, that thou canſt not do, is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>To ſweare in vaine, that is without neceſſity, is a V. S. if yet that which thou doeſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150416:7"/> ſweare be true.</p>
                  <p>To ſay by my fayth, in trueth, or truly, not meaning thereby the fayth or trueth of God, is no oath.</p>
                  <p>To ſay, God helpe me, by this heauen, fire, or other thinges, adding God thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as alſo to ſay by my life, by my ſoule, and the like, is an oath.</p>
                  <p>To ſweare, to accuſe an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with intention ſo to doe, if afterwardes thou do it not, becauſe thou doeſt thinke it not to be done, is not periury nor ſinne; ſo the mother that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150416:7"/> doth ſweare to beat her childe though she doe not beat him, doth not ſinne.</p>
                  <p>To ſweare not to do a thing which in it ſelfe is no ſinne, nor occaſion of ſinne, but is indifferent; as for example, not to weare any more ſuch hoſen, not to play at Teneſſe, not to go with ſuch a one, or in ſuch a houſe or ſtreet, if thou do the contrary it is no M. S. vnleſſe there were any cauſe of M. S. which cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remoued, thou mayſt go.</p>
                  <p>I haue curſed aſwell others, as my ſelf through choler, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150416:8"/> without intention that any e-euill should befall them. It is a V. S. but with a purpoſed minde it is a M. S. The like is to be vnderſtood of curſing the ſoules of thoſe that be dead.</p>
                  <p>I haue called vpon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to helpe me, to carie me awaie, or to doe any harme or good, to my ſelfe or others, without deſire it should be ſo indeed, a V. S. with a ful pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it is a M. S. As alſo to doe him any reuerence, or giue him thy ſoule, is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>Thou shalt tell whither
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150416:8"/> thou haſt blaphemed, or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, Chriſt, or the Saints, and whether thou haſt ſpoken any injurious wordes againſt them, for it is a M. S. And thou muſt vtter what ſort of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, and injuries they were.</p>
                  <p>I haue of purpoſe giuen oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to others, to curſe, or, blaſpheame God, his Saints, or other, men, and haue done and ſpoken things without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny neceſſitie, knowing that by this they would blaſpheame. It is a M. S. The like is to be ſaid of ſcandall, touching that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150416:9"/> that doth concerne a matter of Mortall ſinne, if it be giuen of purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>To curſe the day, the tyme, water, winde, &amp;c. without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to curſe God who hath made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is a V.s. So to curſe Chriſtmas day Eaſter day, &amp;c without mind to curſe the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in thoſe daies, or by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repreſented is a V S.</p>
                  <p>I haue ſpoken injurious &amp; villanous wordes of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, againſt ſome perſon, diffaminge them by this meanes, as calling an honeſt woman a queane, an honeſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150416:9"/> mans ſonne, a baſtard, &amp;c. it is a. M S. but if it be a light matter, it is a V. s. and of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous injuries, he is bound to aske forgiueneſſe, &amp; make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
                  <p>I haue ſpoken euill of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſlaundred them in matters of great waight, by ſaying they haue committed ſome filthie actes, they haue ſtollen, &amp;c. it is a M.S. but in light matters, it is only a V. S.</p>
                  <p>To vtter true things, but yet vnknowen, with minde to diffame any one grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, or ſo that infamie doe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150416:10"/> follow thereof. is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>To ſpeake that which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly knowen, as to ſaie ſuch a woman is a harlot, shee being ſo indeede, is no ſinne: and the like is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of other publike ſinnes, and ſinners.</p>
                  <p>I haue willingly giuen eare to ſuch as ſpeake ill of others, for ſome great hatred or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie. It is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>For one to vaunt him ſelfe to haue committed a M. s. which he hath not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if it be with notable harm of himſelfe or others, or with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150416:10"/> other mens infamie, or with ſome euill intention, or to take pleaſure as if he had done ſuch things, is a M. S. But without theſe conditions, it is a V. s forſomuch as he is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal of his owne fame, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of himſelfe is the owner.</p>
                  <p>I haue not heard Maſſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Sundaies, and Holie daies, or haue loſt a great part thereof, without any lawfull cauſe, it is a M. S. So alſo to haue a minde not to heare Maſſe on ſuch daies. Likewiſe to be occaſion that others do not heare it at ſuch times,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150416:11"/> without any lawfull reaſon.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer to talke the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt tyme of maſſe on thoſe daies, or to thinke purpoſely on other affaires at that time, is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>If one doe not faſt being of ſufficient yeares, it is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>To worke vpon Holie daies for much ſpace of time, it is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue borne hatred to my parents &amp; ſuperiours, &amp; wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome great hurt, with a deliberate minde, it is a M. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue not obeyed my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and superiours, in that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150416:11"/> which appertaineth to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of their family &amp; goods, if it be aduiſedly and with contempt, it is a M. S. otherwiſe it is Veniall, in ſmal matters, but it is a M. S. in matters of importance.</p>
                  <p>I haue diſobeyed my ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours and Rulers in ſuch things as belong to good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to the ſaluation of my ſoule, as to flie ſcandalls; plaies that be forbidden, and the like it is a M. S. so likewiſe if one doe thinke it to be a shame that he is borne of ſuch Parents, or to be taken for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150416:12"/> their child, if it comes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, but if it be to auoyde greater incommodity, it is not a mortall ſinne.</p>
                  <p>I haue bene at variance, I haue ſtroken others, fought with them, and throwen at them, &amp;c. with intention to doe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> notable harme, it is a M. S. but without ſuch inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in light things, it is a V. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue borne hatred to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wishing them ſome great dommage, it is a M. s. but in light matters, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intention of euill, it is a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150416:12"/> Veniall ſinne,</p>
                  <p>To reueale a ſecreat with notable hurt, or with minde to domage thy neighbour, is a M. S. As alſo if thou diddeſt ſweare not to reueale it.</p>
                  <p>To commit any carnall and filthie acte with thine owne ſelfe, it is a Mortall ſinne. And if at the ſame time, thou hadſt thy minde ſet vpon any man or woman &amp;c. If thou doe not vtter this circumſtance in Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Confeſſion is of no valewe.</p>
                  <p>Thou muſt alſo Confeſſe, if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150416:13"/> thou haſt ſinned with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and with what ſort of perſons. Likewiſe of touching others, of kiſſing, of promiſe, of vncleane wordes to any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill ende: all be M. S. As alſo all deſires to ſinne, when there is a full purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>I haue had carnall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and haue taken pleaſure, and bene glad of them, &amp; this willinglie. They are alwaies M. s. but not if they be againſt our will, and doe diſpleaſe vs, and that we ſeeke to be ridde of them, as ſpeedilie as wee may: but if we were a
<pb facs="tcp:150416:13"/> little negligent, they are V: s. and it is expedient alwaies to Confeſſe them.</p>
                  <p>I haue deſired to be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of men or woemen, to an ill ende. I haue caſt my ſight, here and there, and wandered vp and downe, to accomplish my ill deſire, and would haue fulfilled the ſame, if I had could. I haue decked and trimmed my ſelfe for this purpoſe. I haue read &amp; ſong, laſciuious &amp; wanton things, tending to the ſame ende. Theſe thinges are alwaies Mortall ſinne, when there is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150416:14"/> a deliberate minde.</p>
                  <p>I haue had pollution in my ſleepe, without any faulte of mine, and was afterwarde diſcontented that I had it. It is no ſinne. But when willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie there is occaſion giuen, or when we take pleaſure of it, as of an ill act, it is a M. s.</p>
                  <p>So likewiſe when we doe wish or deſire, that a filthie carnall dreame had bene true indeede. As alſo the pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that a man hath being waking, through his owne fault, by thinking, looking, or touching others, or him:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150416:14"/> ſelfe, is a <hi>M. S.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To ſinne with brute beaſtes, or to take carnall delite by touching or behoulding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. is M. S.</p>
                  <p>I haue taken other mens goods, and haue deceaued them in matters of importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it is M. S. So likewiſe to take any thing of moment in the houſe where we dwel, againſt the will of thoſe that be ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours in that howſe, and it is called domeſticall or houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thefte: in a ſmall matter it is V. S. with mind to ſteale much, it is a M. s.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:150416:15"/>
                  <p>I haue deſired other mens goods vnjuſtlie, and to doe them ſome great dammage, and this with a full purpoſe: it is a <hi>M. S.</hi> but not when one doth deſire to haue as great goods as another, without harme or dammage to him.</p>
                  <p>I haue bin proude: vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and preferring my ſelfe before others, &amp; contemning them.</p>
                  <p>I haue bin vaine glorious, &amp; praiſed my ſelfe: but verie ſleightlie, without harme of anie others, and without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king due honour from God it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150416:15"/> is a V. S. So likewiſe of anger in ſmale thinges, as alſo of Glu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, Couetouſnes, slouth, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer if thou haue committed any other ſinnes, that be not written or ſet downe heere, thou muſt yet Confeſſe them.</p>
                  <p>If one did remaine a whole yeare, with purpoſe to commit mortall ſinne, neuer repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him ſelfe therof all that time, he is in ſtate of mortall ſinne, and ought to Confeſſe how long he hath bin in that ſtate by ſaying, I haue borne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150416:16"/> hatred a whole yeare. I haue had carnall deſires two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths &amp;c.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Certaine aduiſes.</head>
                     <p>NOTE 1. That before thou goe to the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of confeſſion, thou muſt thinke vpon thy ſinnes, and examen thy conſcience wel, reading ſuch thinges as be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heere. Thou maiſt alſo write thy ſinnes, and reade them before thy ghoſtlie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if thy memorie doe not ſerue thee.</p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150416:16"/>
                     <p>Note 2. That to conceale, one mortall ſinne, willinglie, is ſacrilege, and the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is not auaileable, nor of force: as neither that confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which thou doeſt make afterwards, although thou doe confeſſe the ſinne left out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if thou doe not vtter that in thine other confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou dideſt willinglie conceale it: and thou muſt repeate as well the former confeſsion, as all others made in this maner. so likewiſe if thou doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any thing be a mortall ſinne, and doeſt not vtter the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150416:17"/> ſame, it is a M. s. but not if thou leaue to doubt, and art reſolued that it is no M. S.</p>
                     <p>To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceale a Venial ſinne, &amp; not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe it, is no M. S.</p>
                     <p>Note 3. That the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is not of force, if thou haue not a true and full pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to abſtaine from all Mortall Sinne, and true ſorow for thoſe that be paſt: nay thou doeſt ſinne mortallie, if thou goe to Confeſſion with intention to be abſolued in that ſtate: but not if thou goe with a deſire to be holpen of thy ghoſtlie father, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150416:17"/> to doe that which thou oughteſt.</p>
                     <p>Note 4, That thou muſt tell the number of thy Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinnes, as neere as thou canſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, &amp; if willingly thou doe not vtter them, thy Confeſſion is not auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: as alſo if thou doe not manifeſt the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which doe chaunge the nature and kinde of Mortall ſinnes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſufficeth not to ſaie, I haue ſinned with a woman, but is needfull alſo to tell whether shee were kinne to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150416:18"/> thee or no: and if shee were ſuch, then whether she were a virgin, or a married woman, Religious or ſecular, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Note 5. That a man muſt forgoe and leaue the occaſion of M. <hi>S.</hi> as the conuerſation of ſuch perſons, and in ſuch places, where, and with whom, he is wont to ſinne, otherwiſe he may not be abſolued: for that it is a ſigne that he doeth not repent him ſelfe, although he ſaie the contrarie in wordes.</p>
                     <p>Note 6. That it is neceſſarie to reſtore other mens goods,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150416:18"/> as ſoone as may be, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their good name, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is not true which I tould of ſuch, or ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and this to all thoſe to whom it was ſpoken of, if it were falſe: but if it were true, it is ſufficient to praiſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that were ſpoken ill of.</p>
                     <p>Note 7. That if one had bin a meanes, or procured, that any other ſinned mortallie, he muſt needes confeſſe it.</p>
                     <p>Note 8. That if one went into Nuneries forbidden by Excommunication without licence, he is excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150416:19"/> as alſo he haue ſtrooken by diabolicall ſuggeſtion any Religious perſon, or any that had holie orders, or ſuch as had leſſer orders.</p>
                     <p>Note 9. That he which doth examen his conſcience touching the thinge a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, muſt take that onlie which he hath donne, and tell it as it is there ſet downe, that is, whether he did it with a full purpoſe, or no: and the like is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode of lies, whether they were with oathes, or without them, that ſo the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150416:19"/> ghoſtlie father may knowe when it is a M. S. and when not. The which thou shalt ſee, if thou doe finde adjoined therunto theſe letters M. S. and where there is V. S. it ſignifieth a Veniall Sinne: which being vnderſtoode by thee, thou muſt flie mortall ſinnes, and chooſe rather to die then to commit one onlie: as alſo thou muſt eſchue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial ſinnes as much as lieth in thee.</p>
                     <p>Note laſtlie, that a <hi>ſtedfaſt minde, a full purpoſe, a reſolute will, aduiſedlie,</hi> and <hi>with all our
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150416:20"/> hart,</hi> is one thinge, and when this is, it maketh that our thoughts, deſires, words and deedes be mortall ſinne, in matters of importance, and therfore it is needfull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine our wil that it conſent not, but rather to ſaie with our will, <hi>I wil not,</hi> or <hi>no;</hi> for that, where the will hath repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, there cannot be ſinne, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie mortall: wel there may be veniall ſinne, by reaſon of our neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in not reſiſting ſo ſoone as we should. As for example, if there came to thy minde an euil thought, whilſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150416:20"/> thou dooſt not marke it, it is no ſinne: but when thou doeſt reflect vpon it and ſee it, if thou doe caſt it off ſpeedilie, thou doeſt merite therby: and a little negligence in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, doth make it a Veniall ſinne: but voluntarie, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling delighte in the ſame, doth make it mortall, albeit thou hadſt no purpoſe to put it in execution, but onlie to take pleaſure in ſuch a wicked thought. The reſolution to put it in practiſe, dooth make the ſinne greater, and if it be done in deede, it maketh it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150416:21"/> yet greater, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there was the act now reallie donne, it is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t only to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, becauſe in this is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the thought, &amp; the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution made: but if it were a thought, onlie with the delite aforeſaid, it muſt alone be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it paſt</p>
                     <p>Some one perchance will ſay. Sir I can not ſpeedilie rid my ſelfe of ſuch naughtie thoughtes. The anſweare is: that then thou art ſuppoſed to haue caſt them off ſpeedilie, when thy will doth repugne and miſlike of them, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150416:21"/> ſayeth <hi>no</hi> or, <hi>I will not,</hi> albeit ſuch thoughts continued for a whole yeare together, or turned back a thouſand times a day, againſt thy will. The which if it be vnderſtood aright, and as it behoueth, will giue exceeding great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to deuout ſoules, &amp; to thoſe that haue a timerous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, who neuer would conſent to any ſin. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which being free toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with doing good &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly works, we may hope through the grace of almightie God, to arriue to the glorie of heauen, by his infinite mercie. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:150416:22"/>
                     <head>WHAT THE PENI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENT OVGHT TO DOE AFTER he hath examined his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</head>
                     <p>AFter that the penitent hath recollected himſelfe, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and ſet before his eyes, that which his conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce shall tell him, of the ſins which he hath committed ſince his laſt Confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be it either by thoughtes, by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or by workes, he shal excite him ſelfe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition &amp; repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance for his ſinnes, where with he hath defiled the beauty of his ſoule, with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150416:22"/> great confidence in the mercie of God, and in the merits of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood of <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> by the which we are washed from our ſinnes in the Sacrament of Pennance, &amp; with a firme purpoſe of amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; for which effect, let him ſay the prayer following.</p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A deuout prayer to procure Contrition.</head>
                        <p>O Good IESV, good IESV, good IESV. O my hope, my refuge, &amp; my health; haue mercy, haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, haue mercie on me. Alas I am a moſt wicked, and moſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150416:23"/> vnworthie ſinner. I am a moſt vile ſinner. I haue ſinned I haue ſinned, I haue ſinned, and done euill before thee. After a thouſand, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand graces receaued from thee. After a thouſand, and a thouſand promiſes made vnto thee, I am as wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly fallen as before. A thouſand times therefore, haue I deſerued to be euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly damned. Nay, hell it ſelfe hath not ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny punishments, as may worthelie correct my ſinne and iniquitie. Wretch that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150416:23"/> I am, I am vnworthie to be called thy creature. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie whome the earth should beare, or to whom it should afforde any manner of ſuſtenance. O my Lord, I haue juſt occation to shed foorth a riuer of teares, yea rather of blood, then of water. It is truely a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that my harte doth not burſte in ſunder, with vehemence of Contrition, when I conſider the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and enormitie of my ſinne. O would to God, would to God, I had neuer
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150416:24"/> offended. Would to God I had neuer letted thy grace in me. Would to God I had neuer contemned thy mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me. O let it pleaſe thee ſweet IESV, for the ſame thy mercie, once more to washe me with thy pretious blood. Once more to heale me with thy ſacred woundes. Once more to ſanctifie me with thy death and paſſion. O cleanſe me, cleanſe me, cleanſe me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly. Reſtore me the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie which thou gaueſt me in Baptiſme, that I may truly pleaſe thee. Here I make,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150416:24"/> Lorde, in thy preſence, and before all the Angels and bleſſed ſpirits, a firme purpoſe to amend my life. I renounce al ſenſuall delectation. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all vanitie and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. I renounce, and vtterly deteſt, al ſinne and iniquitie. My deere Sauiour, shed foorth thy wrath vpon this my body. Afflict me. Cut me in peeces Burne me in this worlde. Lay thy Croſſe vpon my should<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. I am content with al, only that I neuer more offende thee.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:150416:25"/>
                        <head>A prayer before Confeſsion.</head>
                        <p>O Moſt ſweete Lord, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> fountaine of all mercie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> giue me I beſeeche thee, true Contrition and ſorrowe fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> my ſinnes. Send me the gifte of ſpeech and of veritie, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> may explicate and declare my ſinnes, humbly, ſimply, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> entierely to my ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without either diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or concealing any thing to the end that making an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Confeſſion, I may obtaine a full and perfect abſolution Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150416:25"/>
                        <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                        <p>O Moſt beningne &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Sauiour IESV, I beſeeche thee by the merits of thy bitter Paſſion, that it would pleaſe thee to haue pittie on him whom thou haſt created to thyne image and likenes, and bought by a painfull and dolorous death. O my Lord, who art the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome diuine, let it pleaſe thee to informe me of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of my ſinnes, that I be not deceiued by the ſpirit of lying in the recitall of them,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150416:26"/> which I intend to make to my ghoſtly father, by thee eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished, in vertue of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious bloud to giue me abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. O my Lord, which art the power diuine, driue from me, I beſeech thee, all feare and humane shame, to the end that I be not any wayes withdrawen, to open and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the woundes of my ſoule: grant this by the merits of thy woorthy woundes, ſo many tymes for me opened and renued. Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:150416:26"/>
                     <head>What the penitent is to doe when the Prieſt giueth him abſolution.</head>
                     <p>WHILST the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour shall giue the Abſolution, the Penitent may conſider the great bounty &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, to haue giuen vs this Sacrament, for the washing and Purgation of our ſoules, by the merits of the Paſsion of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: or thinke vpon ſome poynt or article of the Paſsion or ſay ſome briefe jaculatory Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſuch as this which followeth, or the like.</p>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:150416:27"/>
                        <head>A Prayer to be ſaid whilſt the Abſolution is giuen.</head>
                        <p>O My ſweete Lord God, giue me the grace, that there be not in me, any impediment to receaue the true, entire, and totall remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all my ſinnes, by the merite of thy moſt precious blood shed for me vpon the Croſſe, O IESV haue mercie on me. O God be mercifull to me a ſinner. Thou who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feredſt for me, haue mercie on mee.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:150416:27"/>
                        <head>A Prayer after Confeſsion.</head>
                        <p>O My Lord God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy, who haſt called me, &amp; expected my repentance, and comming vnto thee by the Sacrament of Confeſſion, thou haſt gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receaued me, by thy boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, pittie, and mercie, and by the merits of the precious bloud of my Sauiour IESVS, which hath bene applied vnto me in this holy Sacrament. Thou haſt giuen mee the grace to haue Contrition,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150416:28"/> and ſorrow for my ſinnes and faults, which is the firſt part of Penance; Thou haſt giuen me the force and conſtancy to confeſſe them all, ſo farre foorth as I could remember, which is the ſecond. Giue me grace now to fullfill the third, which is Satisfaction, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging me duely, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly, of the payne which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded me, ſo that hauing accomplished the whole my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Penance, I may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued &amp; reckoned amongſt the number of thy true chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, with Saint Peter, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150416:28"/> S. Mary Magdalen, the true mirours of pennance. Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                        <p>O Soueraigne bounty, bottomeleſſe depthe of mercie, and God of all cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie and ſweetnes, it is vnto thee that I come to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my ſelfe: vnto thee I make my refuge, hauing vnfoulded my faults in the Sacrament of Confeſſion, and diſcharged my ſelfe of the great burthen of my ſinnes, which did ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much oppreſſe my ſoule, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of I giue thee moſt humble
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150416:29"/> thankes, and I beſeech thee, to confirme in my ſpirit the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of ſaluation, which thou haſt giuen me by newnes of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, the which hereafter thou maiſt make to grow in me by thy holy grace. O let it pleaſe thee for the time to come, to ſupport me by thy power, to the ende that I fall not into the ſnares of mine enemies, who ſeeke euery moment to deuoure me. I call, o Lord, for thy helpe, helpe me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the world, the flesh, &amp; the diuel, that I may keep &amp; preſerue me in the obſeruance
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150416:29"/> of thy holy commandements, and diligently, humbly, and deuoutly ſerue thee, and laud thee, by the bloud and merits of IESVS CHRIST thy Son, to whome with thee and the Holy Ghoſt, be all prayſe and glory. Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:30"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:30"/>
                  <p>CERTAINE VERY PIOVS AND GODLY CONSIDERATIONS.</p>
                  <p>Proper to be exerciſed, whilſt the incruentall Sacrifice of the Maſſe is celebrated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SET FORTH For the comfort and benefite of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> deuout Catholikes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By IOHN HEIGHAM.</p>
                  <p>ANNO 1624.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:31"/>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:150416:31"/>
                  <head>THE MANNER HOVV TO HEARE MASSE. AND FIRST, Of the Ornaments appertayning to the Prieſt.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Amice.</head>
                     <p>WHEN the Prieſt put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the <hi>Amice</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes: I wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> conſider the cloath wherew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> the Iewes did blind-fould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150416:32"/> eyes of Chriſt, &amp; buffet him on the face ſaying. <hi>Prophecie vnto vs, O Chriſt, who was he that ſmit thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the ſame.</head>
                     <p>VVhen he puteth the ſame <hi>Amice</hi> vpon his head. I will conſider the sharpe Crowne of thornes, which was ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t vpon our Sauiours head, which peirced his braines, to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding torment.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Albe.</head>
                     <p>VVhen he putteth on the <hi>Albe.</hi> I will conſider the longe white garment, wherin Chriſt being cloathed, they mocked
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150416:32"/> him, deſpiſed him, and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him for a foole.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Gyrdle.</head>
                     <p>VVhen he puteth on the <hi>Gyrdle.</hi> I wil cal to minde how they ſtreightly bound the handes of our Lord behinde him, and like a notorious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor, led him from place to place, and from one Iudge to another.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Manuple.</head>
                     <p>VVhen he putteth on the <hi>Manuple:</hi> I will conſider the cordes wherewith they tyed that innocent LAMBE, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> he was lamentably whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:150416:33"/> and ſcourged at the Pillar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Stole.</head>
                     <p>When he putteth on the <hi>Stole:</hi> I will conſider the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy Croſſe, which was layde vpon our Sauiours shoulders: as alſo the ropes wherwith he was ignominiouſly haled to the Mount of Caluary.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the veſtement.</head>
                     <p>VVhen he putteth on the <hi>Veſtement:</hi> I will conſider the purple Garment wherewith being reueſted, in moſt pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner he was shewed of PILATE to the people, ſaing, <hi>Ecce homo.</hi> Behold the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150416:33"/> man.</p>
                     <p>And I at the putting on of theſe, will beſeech our LORD to graunt vnto me; The <hi>Amice</hi> of Sufferance; The <hi>Albe</hi> of cleane conuerſation; The <hi>Girdle</hi> of chaſtitie; The <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuple</hi> of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancy. The <hi>Stole</hi> of Obedience. And the <hi>Vesteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> of Charity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Introibo, or entrie to the Maſse.</head>
                     <p>WHen the Prieſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth the <hi>entrie to the Maſſe.</hi> I will conſider the great dignity and woorthin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f this holy Sacrifice, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150416:34"/> mine owne greate vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be preſent at the ſame. And I will beſeeche our Lord that I may woorthelie asiſt thereat, and that him ſelfe would put thoſe woordes into my mouthe, and thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions into my harte, which as his owne, may both be heard, and receiued of him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Confiteor.</head>
                     <p>VVhen he ſayeth the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteor.</hi> I wil conſider the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our firſt parents; the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of al the world; and myne owne offences. Of all which I will moſt hartilie aske forgi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:150416:34"/>
                     <head>Of kiſsing the Altar.</head>
                     <p>VVhen he approacheth to the <hi>Altar</hi> &amp; <hi>kiſſeth</hi> the ſame. I will conſider the Incarnation of CHRIST, and the vnion of mans nature, with the word Eternall; And further, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall vnion of euery ſoule with his Lord IESVS: which vnion of my ſoule with my Sauiour, I alſo will deſire.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the introite.</head>
                     <p>WHen the <hi>Intr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> is ſaide; I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uent deſire of the Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150416:35"/> for the comming o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> CHRIST. And I alſo will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that he will vouchſafe to come vnto me, and to dwell in my ſoule.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Kyrie eleiſon.</head>
                     <p>VVhen <hi>Kyrie eleiſon</hi> is ſaid, I will beſeech the three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine perſons, the Father, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sonne, and the Holie Ghoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to haue mercie vpon me, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vpon the whole world.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Gloria in excelſis.</head>
                     <p>VVhen <hi>Gloria in excelſis</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſaid. I will imagine that I ſee the childe IESVS borne in the manger and to heart the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150416:35"/> holie Angels ſing this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hymne. With whom I wil indeauour to prayſe our Lord and to render him thanks for ſo great a benefit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Dominus vobiſcum.</head>
                     <p>VVhen <hi>Dominus vobiſcum</hi> is ſayed. I will call to minde how our <hi>Sauiour manifested</hi> himſelfe <hi>to the three Kinges,</hi> and in them to all the Gentiles. And I will pray him that he will alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelfe to me, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though moſt vnworthy and full of miſcry.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the firſt Collects</head>
                     <p>VVhen the firſt <hi>Collects</hi> are
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150416:36"/> ſayed. I will conſider how Chriſt, at twelue yeares age, went vnto the temple to pray and to worship his heauenly Father: &amp; how his B. Mother with great ſorrowe, ſought him three dayes together, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing she had loſt him. And I will beſeech him, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I looſe him by my ſinne, I may by true Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Confeſſion and Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, neuer ceaſe to ſeeke him vntill I finde him, in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of my ſoule.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Epiſtle.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> is read
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150416:36"/> I will remember S. IOHN Baptiſt, how he remayned in the wildernes, and preached vnto the people that the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias was come. I will call to minde alſo, how CHRIST was baptiſed of him, and began to preach the Goſpell to the Iewes, who yet receaued no fruit thereby: and I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my ſelfe to be worſſe then they, for that by the doctrine of our Sauiour and his Saintes, I haue ſo little amended my life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of remouing the Booke.</head>
                     <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Booke is remoued.</hi> I
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150416:37"/> will feare: conſidering how Chriſt forſaking the Iewes, turned to the Gentiles: and will humbly beſeech him that he will neuer forſake me, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though far vnworthie of his grace and mercie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Ghospell.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>Ghoſpell</hi> is read I will thinke of the Conuerſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of the holie Apoſtles, and o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Diſciples of our Lord by his preaching vnto them and of the wonderfull zeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of their hartes, who forſooke al that they had to followe him: and I will deſire of God
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150416:37"/> to increaſe in me faith, and his holie grace, wherby I may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all, to followe IESVS CHRIST my Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Creede.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the <hi>Creed</hi> is rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. I will conſider the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Gentils which were illuminated with the light of fayth by the preaching of the Ghoſpell: and I will inſtantly beſeeche Almighty God, to giue me that holy light, and liuely fayth, with which I may beleeue, all the myſteries of the Catholike fayth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:150416:38"/>
                     <head>Of Dominus vobiſcum.</head>
                     <p>When <hi>Dominus vobiſcum</hi> is ſayed. I will conſider how our Lord did manifeſt his power, wiſedome, and goodnes, in working ſo many miracles, in healing ſo many infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, and in rayſing the dead: and I will beſeech him that he will rayſe me to a new feruour and loue of him, and with his power and grace, heale all the diſeaſes of my ſoule.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Offertory.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>Offertory</hi> is read, and the Hoſt is offered: I wil conſider that moſt prompte
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150416:38"/> will, wherewith our Lord in euery action of his life, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne himſelfe to his Father, eſpecially in offering himſelfe to ſuffer his paſſion and death for my ſake: with which obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I will alſo offer my ſelfe, with deſire to fulfill his diuine pleaſure, and patiently to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all aduerſityes, yea death it ſelfe for his honor and glory.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the mingling of water with VVine</head>
                     <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Water</hi> is mingled with the <hi>wine:</hi> I will conſider the ſtreight vnion which is betwixt Chriſt our Lord and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150416:39"/> his Church: And I will deſire that vnſeperable vnion bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt my ſoule &amp; my Sauiour IESVS.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Washing the Priestes fingers</head>
                     <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prieſt <hi>Washeth</hi> the endes of his fingers. I wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the great puritie &amp; cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes, which is required in handling and receiuing the body of Chriſt: and I will ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beg of him, to graunt the ſame to me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Orate fratres.</head>
                     <p>When <hi>Orate fratres</hi> is fayed I will meditate on this admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition as made by Chriſt to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150416:39"/> me, and from thence forth I will raiſe vp my ſelfe more feruently to prayer and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the reſt of the Maſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the ſecret Collect.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>Secret</hi> is ſayed. I will conſider how our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſome fewe dayes before his Paſſion, with-drue him ſelfe in ſecret from the malice of the Iewes, And how his owne diſciple conſented to ſell and deliuer him into their wicked handes. And I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche our Lord, neuer to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt me to ſell him to my proper deſires as heretofore I
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150416:40"/> haue done, nor to deliuer him into the handes of my diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate pleaſures.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Preface.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>Preface</hi> is ſayed. I wil conſider the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming back of our Sauiour to Hieruſalem vpon Palme sunday, and I will imagine to heare the voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the children, crying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loude. <hi>Bendictus qui venit in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Domini, Oſanna in excelſis.</hi> Bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of our Lord, Oſanna in the higheſt. And I with gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ioy &amp; preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe my ſelfe to receiue my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:150416:40"/>
                     <head>Of the Canon.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>Canon</hi> is ſayed. I will conſider the prayer which our Lord made in the Garden and there, in ſteede of ſweat, did shed an infinit number of droppes of blood. And I will offer this his bloodie ſweat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of the teares which I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not, &amp; which for the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my hart I can not shed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the firſt Memento.</head>
                     <p>When the firſt <hi>Memento</hi> is ſayed. I will remember the great mindfulnes &amp; care which our Sauiour had of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, in the mideſt of this his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150416:41"/> agonie: &amp; how he aroſe &amp; we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and finding them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, exhorted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pray. And I will the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber al tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by charitie, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, or dutie, I am bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to pray.</p>
                     <p>As for the whole Catholique Church of Chriſt. For the chiefe Paſtor thereof. For all Eccleſiaſtical, and religious par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. For peace and vnitie amongſt all Chriſtian Kinges and Princes. For the conuerſion of all Infidels, Hetiques, and Sciſmatiques. for your Father, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, husband, wife, children, brothers ſiſters, kinsfolkes, benefactors, frendes and enimies, and for all that are in the ſtate of mortall ſinne. For all that are perſecuted, impriſoned, fallen, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or tempted. For all poore, diſtreſſed ſick, and diſeaſed perſons. For all labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, bond ſeruantes, trauellers, and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150416:41"/> For al poore widdowes, fatheries children, and women in childbirth. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally for the fruites of the earthe, for your temporall ſubſtance, &amp; your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation from all dangers, ſoudaine death, fire and all misfortunes. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending any of theſe, or any other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, to the grace and mercie of our Sauiour IESVS, and to the merits of his pretious death and paſſion, applied vnto vs by the meanes of this Sacrifice.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of extending the Prieſtes handes ouer the Chalice.</head>
                     <p>When the Prieſt <hi>extendeth his handes</hi> ouer the Chalice. I will conſider how<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſt for me was taken, bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>, ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, condemned to die, &amp; alſo forſaken of his diſciples. And
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150416:42"/> I will remember, that for me he ſuffered all theſe thinges, and yet haue I oft forſaken him for feare of trouble.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Croſſes made vpon the Host and Chalice.</head>
                     <p>When he maketh the <hi>Croſſes</hi> vpon the Hoſt and Chalice: I will thinke how that great croſſe was prepared and layed vpon the shoulders of my Lord, who carryed it to the mount of Caluary, where he was nayled to the ſame: and I wil craue ayde of him to beare my croſſe, and that with the nayles of his loue, he would
<pb facs="tcp:150416:42"/> tranſpeirce my hart.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the eleuation of the Hoſt.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>Host</hi> is lifted vp. I will conſider how that moſt noble &amp; pretious body of my Lord and Sauiour IESVS, was lifted vp vpon the Croſſe for my ſaluation. And I wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche him to lift vp my ſoule to him, that I may truely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thoſe his wounderfull paines and death, which he did then endure to giue me life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the eleuation of the Chalice.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>chalice</hi> is lifted vp I will conſider the great abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>undance
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150416:43"/> of blood, which flowed forthe of his moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred woundes. And then with great feruour will I offer vp this ſacrifice, to the eternall Father, to his honor and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; and for the remiſſion of myne owne ſinnes, and of the whole worlde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the ſecond Memento.</head>
                     <p>At the ſecond <hi>Memento.</hi> I will conſider, how our Sauiour hanging three houres aliue vpon the Croſſe, at the laſt gaue vp the ghoſt, and his bleſſed ſoule deſcended to the Fathers that were detained in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150416:43"/> Limbo. And I will then pray for N. and N. and for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, that their ſoules may be deliuered from their pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, by the merits of his moſt holie paſſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Nobis quoque peccatoribus.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the Prieſt ſmiteth his breaſt, ſaying. <hi>Nobis quoque peccatoribus.</hi> I wil conſider the great heauines and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Centurion, and of other good people, for the death of our Sauiour, who we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t away ſmiting their brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes for ſorrowe. And I with great contrition, and ſorrowe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:150416:44"/> will bewayle my ſinne, which was the cauſe of this his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of omnis honor &amp; gloria.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>short Eleuation</hi> is made, and the <hi>Hoſt is layd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the corporall.</hi> I will cal to mind the taking downe of my Lord and Sauiour Chriſt from the croſſe, wrapped in a moſt pure and cleane Syndon, and layed in the Sepulcher. And I will beſeech him to cleanſe &amp;c pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify my hart, that he may be burryed therein.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Pater noſter.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the <hi>Pater noſter</hi> is
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150416:44"/> ſayd. I will conſider the prayer which the bleſſed Virgin, the Apoſtles, and other holy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, made in thoſe three dayes: I will thinke on, that great deſire wherwith they did burne to ſee our Lord. And I with them will deſire to ſed my Lord, now glorifyed, in my hart.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Pax Domini.</head>
                     <p>VVhen <hi>Pax Domini</hi> is ſayd. I will contemplate my Lord riſen from the dead, all glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and immortall: and how he appeared to the Bleſſed Virgin, to Marie Magdalen
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150416:45"/> and the holie Apoſtles, ſaying. <hi>Pax vobis:</hi> and I will deſire of him, that he will giue me true peace and quietnes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of diuiding the Host into three partes.</head>
                     <p>When the <hi>Hoſt is divided</hi> into three partes: I wil conſider the holy Church, diuided in three partes, triumphant, militant, and in Purgatoire. And I will beſeeche our Lord, that he wil graunt to me, and to all other, to aſpire to the triumphant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Agnus Dei.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the true <hi>Agnus Dei</hi> is ſayd. I will thinke Chriſt to be
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150416:45"/> the true lambe without ſpot, which S. Iohn Baptiſt did point at with his fingar, by whoſe blood the ſinnes of the worlde are taken away: and I will beſeeche him by vertu of his pretious blood, to cleanſe my ſoule from all ſinne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Prieſtes receuing.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the Prieſt doth? <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate.</hi> I will conſider with what vnſpeakeable glorie and triumphe, our Lord aſcended into heauen in the ſight of all his Apoſtles, vntill at the laſt cloud receiued him. And I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ith moſt inflamed and bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150416:46"/> affection, will ſpiritually communicate with the Prieſt, and make my hart a heauen to receaue my Sauiour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Dominus vobiſcum.</head>
                     <p>VVhen <hi>Dominus vobiſcum</hi> is ſayd. I will conſider, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our Lord be aſcended into heauen, yet he is alwayes preſent with vs in the bleſſed Sacrament. And I will render him thankes for ſo great a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the last Collects.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the laſt <hi>Collects</hi> are ſayd. I will giue moſt great and harty thankes to the holy
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150416:46"/> Trinity, for all his benefits; and eſpecially for that he hath granted me to be preſent, and to be partaker of ſo great a myſtery.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of remouing backe the Booke.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the <hi>Booke</hi> is carried backe to the right end of the Altar. I will thinke how in the end of the world, the Iewes shalbe conuerted to the fayth of Chriſt. And I will pray for the conuerſion of all Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and Infidels.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Dominus vobiſcum.</head>
                     <p>VVhen the laſt <hi>Dominus vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum</hi> is ſayd. I wil imagine to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150416:47"/> heare the ſound of the Angels Trumpe, wherin our Lord in the end of the worlde, will come to Iudgment. And I wil beſeech him, that he wil make me ready and prepared, in that dreadfull day.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Ite miſſa eſt.</head>
                     <p>When <hi>Ite Miſſa eſt</hi> is ſayd. I will recall to minde that, <hi>Goe yee curſed into euerlasting fire,</hi> which shall be ſpoken to the damned: &amp; that, <hi>Come yee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my Father,</hi> which shalbe ſpoken to the ſaued.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the laſt benediction.</head>
                     <p>When the laſt <hi>Benediction</hi> is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150416:47"/> giuen. I will call to minde th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> benediction of Chriſt in that day, which he will giue ouer al the elect, and will leade them with him into paradiſe. And I will beſeech him that he will bleſſe me and all the ſtanders by, who haue aſſiſted with me at this Sacrifice, that both in this world, and the next, we may perpetually prayſe, and glorify his name. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Paternoſter. Aue. Credo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:48"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:48"/>
                  <p>DIVERS DEVOVT CONSIDERATIONS.</p>
                  <p>FOR THE MORE worthy receauing of the Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COLLECTED And gathered, out of ſundry Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and approued Authors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AND Publiſhed for the benefit of all deuout Catholiques, By IOHN HEIGHAM.</p>
                  <p>ANNO 1624.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:49"/>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:150416:49"/>
                  <head>ADVERTISEMENTS FOR THE NIGHT BEFORE RECEIVING</head>
                  <p>THe nighte wherein you meane to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the day following, eate ether nothing, or very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to your ſupper.</p>
                  <p>After ſupper preſently ariſe: ſpend not the time in idle talke, but priuately in your chamber in talke with God.</p>
                  <p>Before you goe to ſleepe, pray vnto God that he woulde
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150416:50"/> keepe you that night from all illuſions of the diuell, from ill ſinne, and hurtfull phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</p>
                  <p>Make choiſe the ſame night, of ſome affection or intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ether one or more, for which you will ſpecially purpoſe to receiue; and often ſtir vp, and renue in your minde, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie thereof.</p>
                  <p>In the morning when you awake, perſuade your ſelfe, that you lie in the armes of Chriſt; and begin to meditate vpon his paſſion: and to recall to mind your former affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:150416:50"/>
                     <head>Of the affections, and inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions for receiuing the B. Sacrament.</head>
                     <p>THe affections and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of thoſe that come to communicate, are ſundrie, according to the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie diſpoſitions of the parties.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued with the loue of God; that they may by meanes of this Sacrament, inuite &amp; bring their beloued vnto them, and delectably embrace him within their foules.</p>
                     <p>Some ar moued by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of their owne infirmitie and weaknes; that they may
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150416:51"/> by the helpe of this heauenly Phiſition, be cured and healed of their diſeaſes.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued therunto by the conſideration of their ſinnes and offences; that by meanes of this diuine Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Sacrifice, they may be purged and pardoned.</p>
                     <p>Some are brought therunto, by reaſon of ſome griefe, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, vexation, or temptation; the end that by the vertue of him who is omnipotent, they may be conforted and deliuered.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150416:51"/> of ſome particular grace; that by meanes of him to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Father denieth nothing, they may obtaine the grace which they deſire.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued with a thankfull acknowledging of ſundrie benefits, which God hath beſtowed vpon them, conſidering that we can not of our parts offer to the Father a thinge of greater thankes, then this Sacrifice of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to praiſe &amp; honor almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God and his Saintes; for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150416:52"/> as we can not honor, nor praiſe him more, then in remembrance of them, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this Sacrifice of praiſe vnto him.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued with an earneſt deſire of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ſaluation, &amp; with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of their afflictions and miſeries; knowing that there is nothing more auaileable in the ſight of the Father, both for the quicke and the dead, then the pretious blood of his only Sonne, which was shed both for the one &amp; the other.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150416:52"/> to ayde and helpe the Church vniuerſall, which are all faithfull people; vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and knowing, that he is a member of that miſtical body wheof IESVS CHRIST is the head, and therefore deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to receiue the ſame, for al thoſe who are woorthy to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue participation therof.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued therunto, to renue the memorie of our Lordes holy Paſsion, and to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der thankes to our merciful redemer, for the ineſtimable woorke of our redemtion.</p>
                     <p>Some are moued with deſire
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150416:53"/> to receiue the true ſpirit of Chriſt, to be made one with him, to be wholy transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and chaunged into him; that they may liue as he liued, in all charitie, obedience, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie of ſpirit, mortification of body, contempt of the worlde, and the like.</p>
                     <p>Finally, ſome are moued with deſire the ſooner to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this worlde, into that glorious and perpetuall habitation of heauen, there to receiue the full fruition and viſion of his diuinitie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:150416:53"/>
                     <head>Of diuers other deuout affections fit for the more worthie receiuing of the B. Sacrament.</head>
                     <p>OTHERS there be, who coming to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doe reſemble them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in their mindes after ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie manners: and by this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes, doe obtaine many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout affections.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes as a prodigal childe; to his Father of pittie.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes as a guiltie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or one comdemned; to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> mercifull Iudge and Sauiour</p>
                     <p>Sometimes as a falſe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> diſloyal ſpouſe, taken in adul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terie;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150416:54"/> to hir louing and tender harted husband.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes as a ſiſter, to hir moſt deare, &amp; cordial brother.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes as a ſtrayed and wandering sheepe; to his good Paſtor.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes as a poore blinde man; to the reſtorer of ſighte.</p>
                     <p>Somtimes as one famished, to the ſweet refectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſoule.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes as one languish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thirſt; to the fountaine of grace, and water of life.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes as one frozen with colde, to the fornace of burning loue.</p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:150416:54"/>
                     <p>Sometimes as a litle infant towardes his nourſe, without whom he can in no wiſe be comforted.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes againe with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to do the greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to God, that euer he did him before.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes to haue greater deuotion, charitie, &amp; loue of God, then euer he had before.</p>
                     <p>In al which to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> arigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and to our better benefit, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> muſt putt vpon vs, as it were the habitt and eſtate of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſelfe ſame perſon, with al othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> circumſtances co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curring the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:150416:55"/> unto.</p>
                     <p>And ſo ſomtimes to vſe one ſometimes another, as God shall moue vs, and as our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition &amp; deuotion shall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs: which alſo we may doe, not only when we shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate ſacramentally, but alwayes as often as we shall heare maſſe, or communicate ſpiritually.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Deuout conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in which God prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth him ſelfe vnto vs, to encourage al fearful &amp; ſcrupulous perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</head>
                     <p>OVR mercifull Lord co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto vs in the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150416:55"/> holy Sacrament, after ſeauen ſundrie maners.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. He cometh in ſuch exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull humilitie, that none is ſo wicked, and vilde a ſinner, but that our Lord God wil come vnto him, and offer him ſelfe (if a man will haue him with him) and will receiue him.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He cometh in ſo great patience, that none is ſo great a ſinner, or ſo much his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, which he will not beare withall, and ſuffer patiently, and if he will reconcile him ſelfe vnto him, be moſt ready
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:150416:56"/> and prepared to remitt him al his faultes, and freely to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. He cometh with ſuch a loue and affection, which he beareth vnto vs, that none is ſo colde and obſtinate, whom he doth not heate (if he wil) in his burning loue.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. He cometh, in ſuch libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, ſo amp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e and copious, that none is ſo poore and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of grace and vertu, whom he may not enrich with the ſtore &amp; plentie of all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſubſtance.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. He giueth him ſelfe in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:150416:56"/> foode moſt delicious, moſt ſweete, and moſt ſufficient, in ſuch ſorte, that none is ſo fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, weake, or famished, that may not be healed, refreshed, ſtrenghtned, and ſuſtained.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. He cometh in ſuch ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and brightnes, that none can be ſo blinded, obſcurſed; or held in ſuch darknes, that may not by his preſence, be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and lightned.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. He cometh in ſuch ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude &amp; aboundance of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that none is ſo indeuout, negligent, and ſlouthful, that may not be awakened ſtirred, &amp; excited to deuotion.</p>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:150416:57"/>
                     <p>O great, and ouer-flowing loue, who is he, who well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering this, wil not maruaile, and with ſighing ſey. <hi>O Lord what is man that ſo thou doeſt viſit him, and ſett thy hart towardes him?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aſpirations to acknowledge our great vnworthines, to receiue the holy Sacrament, of the pretious body and blood of our Sauiour Ieſus.</head>
                     <p>O My Lord, O my God, who art thou, and who am I, that I should preſume to come to receiue thee? The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in heauen doe reuerence
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150416:57"/> thee, and the higheſt powers and glorious Spirits, with trembling doe adore thee. What then shall I doe that am here in earth (duſt and ashes that I am) what shall I doe?</p>
                     <p>O my Lord, o my God, thy only greatnes, doth humble the Angels, although they acknowledg in them no ſinne, nor euill: Yea the higheſt Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins, drawe in their winges, and repute them ſelues like litle flies before thee: what then shall I doe, that am char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the burthen of my iniquitie, but bowe downe my
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150416:58"/> head, proſtrate my ſelfe vpon the earth, and feare to lift vp myne eyes before thee?</p>
                     <p>O my Lord, O my God, if I ſinful wretch had prepared my ſelfe a thouſand yeares by deuout meditations, and had in my ſelfe, the merits of all the iuſt men vpon the earth, and of all the glorious Saintes in heauen, all this were very little, nay nothing to receiue thee according to thy dignity: how much leſſe then, O my Lord, alas how much leſſe shall I doe it, naked that I am of all merits, and charged
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150416:58"/> with an infinit number of ſinnes and vices?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aspirations to craue puritie of minde and conſcience, wher with worthelie to receiue the most B. Sacrament</head>
                     <p>O My Lord, my ſweete Sauiour and my God, who may giue me at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, a pure hart, a cleane hart, a new hart, a hart purged from all ſoyle, a hart ſet on fire with diuine loue, a hart lightned, and shining, with celeſtiall brightnes: ſo that my faire, and delicate ſpouſe Chriſt IESVS coming, he may finde a place
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150416:59"/> of reſt prepared to him in my hart, and nothing which may offende the eyes of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. O that I could (if it were poſſible) receiue thee, ſweete Lord, at this preſent into my ſoule, with that feruour, loue, and affection, wherwith thy worthy and ſacred Mother conceiued thee: and with that deſire, loue and deuotion, that euer thy deuout ſeruants haue receiued, doe receiue, or euer shall receiue thee.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. O that I had in my ſelfe, all the beautie of the nine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:150416:59"/> of Angels, the burning charitie of the Seraphins, the ſanctitie and puritie of the heauenly Saintes, the feruent loue, deuotion, and deſire, of all the choſen frindes of God, which euer were, are, or shall be, ether in heauen or earth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aſpirations to expreſſe a feruent, longing, and impatient deſire of the ſoule, for the coming of our Sauiour in the B. Sacrament.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. O Sweete IESV, ſweete IESV, ſweete IESV, a thouſand times doe I longe for thee, a thouſand times doe I deſire thee, when wilt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150416:60"/> thou come my ſweete Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, when wilt thou come; wheh shall I ſee thee, when shall I feele thee within my ſoule?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. O deare IESV, deare IESV, deare IESV, when shall I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my deſire, poſſeſſe thy bleſſed preſence within my ſoule? when wilt thou come, that I may louingly ioyne my hart to thine? Come therefore, O ſweete IESVS, come O bread of Angels, O heauenly manna, O foode of faithfull ſoules. Come O my ſweete loue, come and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150416:60"/> into thee, all my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, conceptions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde parts, come and rauiſh me from all thinges crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, euen fom my life, euen from my owne ſelfe.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. O diuine fire, come and inflame my hart. O the ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of my ſoule, come quickly vnto me. Wound my hart with thy loue, Come take thy repoſe within my conſcience. Come ſweete IESVS, come quickly, and defer no longer to come. Come the health, the life, and only deſire of my hart.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:150416:61"/>
                     <head>Aſpirations proper to be ſaid whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time of reaming the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, is neere at hande</head>
                     <p n="1">1. O My ſoule, behould thy ſpouſe is coming, ariſe and goe earth to meete him; enter now and ioyne thee neere vnto him; Be glad and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce of the approaching of ſo great a gueſt: becauſe there cometh vnto thee, thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, thy Lord and thy Louer, thy Father, thy Paſtor, and thy Spouſe; Chriſt IESVS thy beloued, he who gaue for thee his deareſt life, that he might redeeme thy ſoule from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:150416:61"/> death.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Open o my ſoule, open the gate to thy Lord and thy God, coming towardes thee; giue place to thy Creator; giue acceſſe to thy ſpouſe, who with ſuch loue approacheth vnto thee.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Them imagin that you heare the ſweete and amiable voice of our Sauiour calling vnto you, and ſaying. Veni amica mea, veni ſponſa mea veni.</hi> Come my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, come my ſpouſe, come vnto me. <hi>To who make anſwere ſaying. Paratum cor meum Deus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ratum cor meum. Ingredere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicte
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150416:62"/> Domine, &amp; miſerere mei.</hi> O God my hart is readie, o God my hart is readie. Enter bleſſed Lord, and haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aſpirations to be ſaid inwardly when the B. Hoſt is in your mouth.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. O Moſt ſweete, moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, moſt faire, moſt noble, moſt highe, moſt ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle, moſt amiable, and moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious IESV. Vouchſafe to enter into the poore houſe of they ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whoſe burning de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is wholy to enioy thee, and whom all the creatures in
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:150416:62"/> heauen and earth, cannot ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie without thee.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. My God, enter into my ſoule and ſanctifie it; enter into my hart &amp; purifie it; my God, enter into my body and countergarde it; and from thy loue neuer ſeparate it.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Into thy handes, o Lord IESV, I commend my ſpirit; to thee I reſigne my life &amp; my ſoule, receiue me, ſweete Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and ſo keepe me, that I neuer eſcape out of thy handes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:150416:63"/>
                     <head>Aſpirations after receiuing, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring the loue of our Sauiour, expreſſed vnto vs in the moſt B. Sacrament.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 I Remember ſweete IESV, the woordes thou ſpakeſt to thine Apoſtles, after thou hadſt washed their feete; ſaing. <hi>Knowe you what I haue done vnto you?</hi> o how wel maiſt thou now ſay vnto me. Knowe you what I haue done vnto you? For what couldeſt thou doe more for me, or what gteater loue, o good IESU, couldeſt thou shew vnto me,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150416:63"/> then firſt to giue this thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to death for me, &amp; now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to giue the ſelfe ſame body and blood in meate &amp; drinke vnto me, in memorie of the ſame thy death?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. O my Lord, what is the cauſe of this thy loue? what meaneth, I pray thee, this Wonderfull loue? Seeſt thou not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how vilde a creature thou haſt caſt thy loue? Wilt thou deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d now once againe into hell? Wilt thou put thy ſelfe now once again into the handes of ſinners to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? wilt thou once againe be
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150416:64"/> borne in a ſtable amongſt bruite beaſtes (meaning your hart?) o ſtrong, o pure, o vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable loue.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Deare Lord, haſt thou perchance lack of ſome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to delight thee (thou that art moſt happy and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in thy ſelfe) that thou ſearcheſt out a little worme of ſo euill life and odor as I? Truly it ſeemeth, as if that thou hadſt neede of thyne owne creature; for thou vſeſt ſuch meanes to obtaine his loue, as though thou couldeſt not be, nor liue without
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:150416:64"/> him. O ineſtimable and moſt ſweete loue, who can but be inflamed of ſo great a loue? what hart can defend it ſelfe, that it be not melted &amp; quite conſumed with this loue?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aspirations expreſsing our loue againe vnto our Sauiour for this ſingular benefitt of the B. Sacrament.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. IF all the riches of the earth were propoſed vnto me; If all the honors and crownes of the worlde; If all the pleaſures and delightes which is poſſible to imagin;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:150416:65"/> with all the knowledge both of men and Angels, I would repute all as dunge, and as meere nothing; I would make no account at al of it, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, O Lord, of this thy ſweete and vnſpeakable loue. 2. If all the creatures in the worlde were in my power, I would moue them all in thy praiſe for this ſingular benefit which haſt beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. If the force and vertu of all men &amp; Angels were alone in me, I would wholy employ them all to magnifie thee, for this thy eſpecial loue vnto me.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:150416:65"/> 4. Lord, Lord, thy loue doth draw me, thy loue doth wound me, thy loue doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uishe me. O that I had in me the puritie of Angels, and the inflamed and burning deſires of all the B. Saintes. O that I had a thouſand hartes to shed foorth in thy loue, and to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to this ſo great a loue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aspirations very feruent, into which the ſoule burſteth forth in great admiration of the B. Sacrament.</head>
                     <p>O Bread of life, O bread of Angels, O ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150416:66"/> of ſoules, o ſecret comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of holy mindes! O heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpouſe, O IESVS CHRIST my delectable loue! O riches of the ſoule! O ſolace of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted O foode of the famis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed! O my ioy, O my glorie, and al my beatitude!</p>
                     <p n="2">2. O meeke lambe, O milde maieſtie! O highe charitie, o lowe humilitie! o great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, o bottomles depthe of incomprehenſible bountie! o my Lord, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> much am I bounde for the good which thou haſt done me, and aboue all, for the maner by
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:150416:66"/> which thou haſt done this good vnto me.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. O heauenly Lord, who ſo much loueſt me. o true Pelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, who in thy blood doſt ſo quicken me. o good Paſtor, who ſo doſt giue thy ſelfe in meate vnto me. o faithfull Keeper, who haſt ſo wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful a care ouer ſuch as thou haſt taken in chardge vnto thee</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aspirations after receauing the B. Sacrament, in vtter detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hatred of ſinne.</head>
                     <p>MY God, my Lord, and ſweeteſt loue, neuer
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:150416:67"/> any more, neuer any more of ſinne; neuer any more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the flesh; neuer any more of the world; neuer any more of vanity. I vtterly deteſt all ſinne whatſoeuer, and to thee only, doe I render my ſelfe; to thee only, will I ſerue &amp; obey for the time to come. To thee only doe I deſire, to liue and die, only graunt that I neuer more offend thee, nor that I euer be ſeparated from thee.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. My God, I haue no greater griefe in the worlde, then to think that heretofore I haue ſo
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:150416:67"/> much offended thee. And to thinke that ſometimes againe I may come to offende thee, cauſeth ſo great a feare in my ſoule, and doth ſo much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict me, that I would wish to die a thouſand deathes to be out of this danger that I neuer any more become thy enimie,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. O my God, permit not, I beſeeche thee, that for the time to come I euer more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe thee. And if thou forſeeſt that ether by frailty or ſuggeſtion of the diuel, liuing yet longer, I shall mortally
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:150416:68"/> offend thee, shew me the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to take me out of the worlde, and that I die before I commit the ſinne actually.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aspirations in which the ſoule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiereth wholy to be withdrawne from all creatures: with a perfect reſignation to God, &amp; altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be gouerned by him.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. O My ſouueraigne and dreadfull Lord, I would wish for the time to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; neuer any more to appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re amongſt men but to hide me, if it were poſſible; vnder the earth, that by this meanes
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:150416:68"/> no earthly creature, may euer regayne my loue from thee, euer withdrawe my hart from thee, or euer ſeparate my affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from thee.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. O myne eyes, what deſire you more to ſee heere? o myne eares, what deſire you more to hearken here? o my toung, what deſireſt thou more to taſt here? o my hart and all my ſences, shut vp, shut vp your gates, shut them vp I ſay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually, to the end that neuer any thinge may haue acceſſe into my ſoule, which may euer diſſolue this ſtreight coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:150416:69"/> betwixt my Sauiour and me.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. O my ſweete and merciful Lord, behould that from this very houre, I doe wholy aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my ſelfe to thy diuine prouidence, and voluntarily and freely, now, and for euer giue, preſent and conſigne my ſelfe, body and ſoule vnto thee deſiring that thou worke in me as it shall pleaſe thee, and al that it shal, pleaſe thee, and that on my part, I neuer giue thee any lett or impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Finally, gouerne all my deſires, &amp; guide al my actions
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:150416:69"/> and workes, ſo that all my workes may render thee obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, honor, and glorie, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Deuout &amp; iaculatorie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceptions very proper to he vſed, in the day wherin one hath receiued the B. Sacrament.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FIRrſt you may burſt foorth in to theſe wordes, in manner of a spirit wholy replenisht and rauisht with ioy, and ſay.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O my ſoueraigne Lord, my Sauiour, my Redeemer, and my God, I haue here the pledge of thy loue, I haue
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:150416:70"/> heere the memoriall of thy death, I haue heere the price of all the world, I haue heere my Lord, my God, and al my good.</p>
                     <p>O wonderfull grace, o won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull grace, to haue myne owne Sauiour incloſed within my ſoule!</p>
                     <p>O my Lord and my God, my ſpirit is ſwallowed vp, and quiet tranſported into thee, it is in a maner wholie melted in to thee, by reaſon of thy loue, and it cauſeth my hart, euen to open it ſelfe at thy preſence, like as the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:150416:70"/> roſe before the ſinne. Than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, thankes, thanks therfore, o my Lord, for ſo infinit, ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable, and vnſpeakable a benefit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>You may ſometimes alſo, by way of a diligent care that you would not offend him, propoſe this dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto your owne hart, ſaying.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Domine est ne cor meum, &amp; corpus meum adhuc mundum in conſpectu tuo?</hi> Lord is my body and my mynde yet cleane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Somtimes againe by way of hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayer that he wold not leaue you, ſaying with the holy Prophet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:150416:71"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ne derelinquas me Domine: Deus meus, ne diſceſſeris à me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Leaue me not, O my Lord: o my God depart not from me.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sometimes likewiſe, you may with great, ioy of spirit recite the ſong of the</hi> 3. <hi>childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> 3. <hi>ſaying</hi>
                        <q>Benedicite omnia opera Domini Domino, laudate &amp; ſuperexaltate eum in ſoecula. &amp;c. Benedicite An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geli Domini Domino: benedicite caeli Domino, &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>All yee workes of our Lord, bleſſe yee our Lord; prayſe and ex tolle him for euer</p>
                     <p>Bleſſe our Lord yee Angels of our Lord: ye heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bleſſe
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:150416:71"/> our Lord, &amp;c. As in the office of our Lady.</p>
                     <p>Moreouer, to exerciſe ſome other actes of greate deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you may ſometimes ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin your ſelfe as one wounded in ſoule with ſundry woundes, and that IESVS CHRIST, the true phiſitian of ſoules, cometh to caſt his woundes vpon yours, to the end per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to heale you.</p>
                     <p>You may likewiſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by imgination, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your ſelfe into the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of a little Bee, mounting vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tree of the Croſſe, &amp;
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:150416:72"/> flying buſily from one wound to another, to gather and ſuck into your ſoule the ſweete, honie of his moſt pretious blood.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A briefe prayer for concluſion.</head>
                     <p>SWeete IESVS by the vertu of this moſt B. Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; I beſeeche thee to roote vp and extirpate in me, all the branches and ſeeds of my euil paſſions, renue me wholy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, ſo that in thee I may take a new force and viguere: and that in vertu of thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, of vicious, which I haue
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:150416:72"/> alwayes bene, I may for time hereafter become vertuous: of a childe of vanitie, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner of the world: of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous, chaſt: of gluttenous, ſober: of ſlouthfull, feruent and diligent: of harſlie, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke, and impatient, ſweet, meeke, and patient: of vnpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, charitable: of proude, humble: of preſumptuous and ill aduiſed, diſcreete and modeſt: of vaine and light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> graue and ſettled: of incon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ant, firme and ſtable: finally, of a ſinner, and enwrapped in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſeries, I may become by thy
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:150416:73"/> grace, juſt, and of exemplar, &amp; holie conuerſation. Graunt this ſweete Sauiour IESV, for thy infinite loue and mercie ſake. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>THE LITANY OF the bleſſed Sacrament.</head>
                     <p>LOrd haue mercie.</p>
                     <p>Chriſt haue mercie.</p>
                     <p>Lord haue mercie.</p>
                     <p>Chriſt heare vs.</p>
                     <p>O Chriſt heare vs.</p>
                     <p>O God the Father of heauen. <hi>Haue mercie vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>o God the Sonne redeemer
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:150416:73"/> of the world. <hi>Haue mercie vpon vs</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O God the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Haue mercie vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O holie Trinitie one God. <hi>Haue mercie, vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Liuely Bread that didſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from heauen. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>God hidden, and my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>Haue mercie vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Bread of the elect. <hi>Haue</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Wine budding foorth vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins. <hi>Haue mercie vpon vs</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fruitfull Bread, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of kinges. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Holie Sacrifice. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pure oblation. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:150416:74"/>
                     <p>Lambe without ſpot <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Table of propoſition <hi>Haue. mercie vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moſt pure Table. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Foode of Angels. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hidden Manna <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Memoriall of the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull woorkes of God. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Superſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tial bread. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Woorde made flesh, and dwelling in vs <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Holy hoſt. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chalice of benediction. <hi>Haue mercie vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Myſterie of faithe. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moſt highe and venerable Sacrament. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:150416:74"/>
                     <p>Sacrifice of all other moſt holy. <hi>Haue mercie vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Truly propitiatorie for the quick and dead. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Preſeruatiue, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are preſerued from ſinne. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Miracle aboue al others aſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onishing. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moſt ſacred co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration of our Lordes death. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Gift ſurpaſſing al fulnes. <hi>Ha</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chiefe memoriall of diuine Loue <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Abundance of diuine boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Holie, and moſt majeſticall
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:150416:75"/> myſtery. <hi>Haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Medicine of immortallity. <hi>Haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Dreadful and life-giuing Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Bread of the Almighty word, made flesh. <hi>Haue</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Vnbloudy Sacrifice. <hi>Haue</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moſt ſweet banquet, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the miniſtring Angels attend. <hi>Haue</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sacrament of Piety. <hi>Haue</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Bond of Charity. <hi>Haue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Offerer, and oblation. <hi>Haue</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Spirituall ſweetnes taſted in his proper fountaine. <hi>Haue</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:150416:75"/>
                     <p>Refection of holy ſoules. <hi>Haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Voyage food of thoſe which dye in our Lord. <hi>Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pledge of future glory. <hi>Haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Be mercifull. <hi>Spare vs o Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Be mercifull. <hi>Heare vs o Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>From the vnworthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thy body &amp; blood <hi>Deliuer vs o Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>From concupiſcence of the flesh. <hi>Deliuer vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>From concupiſcence of the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:150416:76"/> eyes. <hi>Deliuer vs</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>From pride of life. <hi>Deliuer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>From all occaſion of ſinne. <hi>Deliuer vs o Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By that deſire wherewith thou deſieredſt to eate this Paſſeouer with thy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. <hi>Deliuer vs o Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By thy great humility, wherewith thou dideſt washe the feete of thy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. <hi>Deliuer vs o Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By thy burning Charitie, wherwith thou dideſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine this diuine Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Deliuer vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By thy moſt pretious blood
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:150416:76"/> which thou haſt left vnto vs vpon the Altar. <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By the fiue woundes of this thy moſt holy body, which thou receiuedſt for vs. <hi>Deliuer vs o Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We ſinners. <hi>Doe beſeech thee to heare vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That thou wouldſt increaſe &amp; keepe in vs true faith, reuerence, and deuotion of this holy Sacrament. <hi>VVe beſeech thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That thou wouldſt voutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to bring vs to the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vſe of this holie Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:150416:77"/> by true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of our ſinnes. <hi>VVe beſeech.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That thou wouldeſt vout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chſafe to deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all hereſie, infidelitie, &amp; blindnes of hart. <hi>VVe beſeech thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That thou wouldſt voutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to impart vnto vs the pretious &amp; heauenly fruites of this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament <hi>VVe beſeech thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That in the hower of our death, thou wouldſt ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and defend vs with this heauenly viaticum. <hi>VVe beſeech thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:150416:77"/>
                     <p>Sonne of God. <hi>VVee beſeech.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Lambe of God which takeſt awaye the ſinnes of the world. <hi>Spare vs o Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Lambe of God which takeſt awaye the ſinnes of the world. <hi>Heare vs o Lond.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Lambe of God which takeſt awaye the ſinnes of the world. <hi>Haue mercie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>THE PRAYER.</head>
                     <p>O God, who vnder this wonderfull Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t haſt left vnto vs the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of thy paſſion, Graunt vs ſo to woorship the ſacred
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:150416:78"/> myſteries of thy body and blood, that we may continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally feele in vs the fruit of thy redemption: who liueſt and raigneſt with God the Father, in vnitie of the holy Ghoſt, one God for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>This which followeth may be fitlie ſayed when the benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the B. Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or coming to adore before the Tabernacle, or Altar, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the ſame is reſerued.</head>
                     <p>IN the name of IESVS euery knee bow, of the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtials, terreſtrials, and infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:150416:78"/> and euery tongue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that our Lord IESVS CHRIST is in the glorie of God the Father. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10.</p>
                     <p>And lett all the people ſay, Amen, Amen. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.47.</p>
                     <p>Who ſhall not feare the o Lord, &amp; magnifie thy name becauſe thou only art holie, becauſe all natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s shal come &amp; adore in thy ſight, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thy judgments be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. <hi>Apocalip.</hi> 15.4.</p>
                     <p>And lett all the people ſay, Amen. Amen.</p>
                     <p>The lambe that was ſlaine is worthie to receiue power,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:150416:79"/> &amp; ſtrenght, &amp; honor, &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, &amp; benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5.12</p>
                     <p>And lett all the people ſay, Amen, Amen.</p>
                     <p>Thou art worthie o Lord to take the booke and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeales thereof: becauſe thou waſt ſlaine and haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs to God in thy blood, out of euery tribe, &amp; tongue, and people, &amp; natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Apo.</hi> 5.9.</p>
                     <p>And lett all the people ſay, Amen, Amen.</p>
                     <p>Thou art worthie o Lord our God to receiue glorie, &amp; honor, and power, becauſe
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:150416:79"/> thou haſt created al thinges, and for thy wil they were, &amp; haue bin created. <hi>Apo.</hi> 4.11.</p>
                     <p>And let all the people ſay, Amen, Amen.</p>
                     <p>Bleſſed be our Lord God of Iſrael, world without end, and let all the people ſay. Amen, Amen.</p>
                     <p>Praiſe, and glorie, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is to our God. Amen.</p>
                     <p>To the king of the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, immortall, inuiſibIe, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, honor, &amp; glorie, for euer and euer. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. Amen.</p>
                     <p>To the only God our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:150416:80"/> by IESVS CHRIST our Lord be glorie and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificence, empyre and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wre before all worldes, and now and for al worldes euer more. <hi>Iude</hi> 25. Amen.</p>
                     <p>Benediction, and glorie, and wiſedome, and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, honor, and power, &amp; ſtrength to our God for euer and euer. <hi>Apocalyps.</hi> 7.12. Amen.</p>
                     <p>Saluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our God which ſitteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the throane, and to the lambe. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.10.</p>
                     <p>To him that ſitteth in the throne, and to the lambe,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:150416:80"/> benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and honor, and glorie, and power for euer. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5.13. Amen.</p>
                     <p>To thee, IESV CHRIST, be glorie for euer. Amen <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36.</p>
                     <p>To thee, IESV CHRIST, be honor, and glorie foreuer and euer. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.</p>
                     <p>To thee IESV CHRIST, be glorie, and empire for euer and euer. Amen. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11.</p>
                     <p>To thee, IESV CHRIST, be glorie, for euer and euer. Amen. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.18.</p>
                     <p>To thee, IESV CHRIST,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:150416:81"/> be honor, and empyre euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Amen. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</p>
                     <p>To thee, IESV CHRIST, be glorie both now and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the day of eternitie. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.</p>
                     <p>Grace with all that loue our Lord IESVS CHRIST in incorruption. Amen. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.24.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:81"/>
                  <p>CERTAINE ADVERTISMENTS TEACHING MEN HOW TO LEAD A Chriſtian life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Written in Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by S.</hi> CHAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LES BOROMEVS, <hi>Cardinall of Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>FOR IOHN HEIGHAM. <hi>Anno</hi> 1624.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:150416:82"/>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:150416:82"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOR.</head>
                  <p>OVr nature being now cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted through ſin, is of it ſelfe ſo bent and inclined to euill, that we doe eaſilie forgett, and leaue to doe good. For this cauſe we haue great neede of helps and encouragements, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby to liue well; and of ſome
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:150416:83"/> one that continuallie may putt vs in minde thereof. To this end may ſerue certaine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſments or counſels gathered here together, that by often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ading them, eache one as in a glaſſe, may in ſome part behould the forme and rule of Chriſtian life, and therin conſider as well what he doth wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as alſo what he ought to doe.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:150416:83"/>
                  <head>GENERALL ADVERTISMENTS.</head>
                  <p>THE chiefeſt thinge that we muſt procure, and to which moſt of al we muſt haue an eye, is to obtaine the grace of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and to keep our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in the ſame, ſeeing that it is impoſſible without Gods grace, to liue Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anlie.</p>
                  <p>To this wil helpe excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinglie, that we haue alway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in our hearts the feare of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:150416:84"/> God, which is the beginning of our ſaluation and of all good; taking great care that we doe not any thing, which may offend his moſt pure and diuine eyes.</p>
                  <p>Haue God therefore all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before thine eyes, in whoſe ſight thou doſt ſtand and who continuallie doth behould thee.</p>
                  <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider often with thy ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, the end for which thou waſt created, which is to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the gloire of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and that thou muſt goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>words this, and al other cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:150416:84"/> further thee thereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to</p>
                  <p>Thinke oftentimes vpon that which is to follow after, to witt perpetuall ioy in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auen, or in hell euerlaſting paine.</p>
                  <p>Be zealous of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; not onlie to obſerue with all diligence his holie commandements, but alſo that his diuine name be not blaſphemed, nor any irreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence done thereunto by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>Beare great reſpect and honour to all things that appertaine to God, and to al
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:150416:85"/> the orders of the holy Church, &amp; of thy paſtor, procuring to obſerue them intirelie as much as lieth in thee.</p>
                  <p>Haue great confidence &amp; truſt in our Lord, that hee wil diſpoſe alwayes that, which shall be moſt for thy good and profit.</p>
                  <p>Haue ſtill an eye the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, eſteeming that nothing doth befall vs without his holie will and pleaſure, and that all is to drawe ſome good thereby.</p>
                  <p>Exerciſe thy ſelfe in the
<pb facs="tcp:150416:85"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150416:86"/>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:150416:86"/> knowledge of thy ſelfe, of thine owne vileneſſe baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and miſerie, flying all ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſelfe reputation, &amp; other vanities of the world. Doe thou neuer truſt to much to thine owne iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but remitt thee eaſily to the iudgment of others, and take counsell ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times of ſpirituall and diſcreete perſons.</p>
                  <p>Procure to be thankfull to God for ſo many benefits, as thou haſt receaued at his hands, acknowledging them and giuing thankes, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoring
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:150416:87"/> to liue wel, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to giue him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment.</p>
                  <p>Take thou not ſo much care to pleaſe men, as to ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſe God. And haue alwayes an eye to that, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to his greater glorie and ſeruice.</p>
                  <p>Expect the rewarde of all thy paines of God, and not of the world.</p>
                  <p>In the buſines and affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res which thou haſt to doe, haue an intention, not to doe anie thinge which is not lawfull, and to doe all that thou doeſt for the loue of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:150416:87"/> God, for in this ſorte shall thy workes bee all meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
                  <p>Acknowledge and ponder with thy ſelfe, that we haue no greater riches nor treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, nor any thinge more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent or of more profite, then to loue God; &amp; that all the reſt doth paſſe away as winde, ſmoke and shadowe.</p>
                  <p>Obey willinglie &amp; readie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, in all things that be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, to all thy Superiours euen ſuch as be temporall: &amp; beare them due reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and reſpect.</p>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:150416:88"/>
                  <p>Endeauour, what lieth in thee, to maintaine peace &amp; quietnes at home in thy houſe as much as may be poſſible: liuing in charitie with al ſorte of people, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be maried, or in any other ſtate.</p>
                  <p>Procure with Gods grace to refraine &amp; bridel thy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in ſuch things as daylie fall out, either at home or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, &amp; not to be at deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te with any one, that ſo thou fall not into greater incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences.</p>
                  <p>Be mindfull to ſupport the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:150416:88"/> faults of others, be they do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtical, or external, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuch manner, as thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt that others should bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re with thee.</p>
                  <p>Remember well that thou art a Chriſtian, and that for this reſpect, thou oughteſt, for the loue of chriſt, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer patientlie ſuch injuries as be done vnto thee, yea to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them: and that which more is, to render good for euill, and to praie for thine enimies, and thoſe that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute thee.</p>
                  <p>In thy tribulations and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:150416:89"/> be mindfull to flie to prayer, &amp; accept of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſcourges, bee they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal or particular, &amp; of al things els that doe happen contrarie to thy expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as coming from the hands of our Lord.</p>
                  <p>Diſpoſe thou ſo of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this worlde, as if thou wert Gods factor, or ſteward, and not abſolute Lord of the ſame: and vſe what thou haſt for neceſſitie and neede, but not for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; &amp; procure ſo to paſſe thorough theſe temporall
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:150416:89"/> things, that thou looſe not thoſe that bee eternall.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer action of thine, make the ſigne of the Croſſe, and haue great confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the vertue thereof.</p>
                  <p>Thou shalt not beginne any affaire of importance, without making firſt thy prayer, and taking alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of thy ghoſtly father, or of ſome other diſcreete &amp; godlie perſons.</p>
                  <p>Sometimes in the yeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke of ſome one, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt greatly truſt, what opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:150416:90"/> hee hath of thy life; and bethinke thy ſelfe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou be in the right way to ſaluation or not.</p>
                  <p>See that thou diſpoſe and diſtribute the howers of the day, according to thy diuers affaires; as for example to praie, to heare Maſſe, to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, to take thy refectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſo thou shalt not looſe time.</p>
                  <p>Blaſphemous and disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſpeeches, ought to be paſſing farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mouth of a Chriſtian man.</p>
                  <p>Beware of an euil cuſtome to ſweare, albeit it were with
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:150416:90"/> truth.</p>
                  <p>Eſchewe al kinde of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and forbidden artes.</p>
                  <p>Doe not eaſilie judge thy neighbour, chiefelie his inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but haue regard to thine owne ſinnes and imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions.</p>
                  <p>Take heede thou be not deſirous nor curious, to know other mens doings: &amp; beware of all ſort of nouelti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, eſpecially in matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to beleefe, as alſo to ſpeake of that which thou doſt neither knowe, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</p>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:150416:91"/>
                  <p>See that thou doe not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, nor ſpeake euill of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor diminish the good name of any one.</p>
                  <p>Doe thou neuer relate, not report any thinge to others, which may trouble their peace &amp; quietnes, or breede any diſſenſion amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Beware of idle words, and much more of ſuch as be diſſolute and dishoneſt.</p>
                  <p>Auoide al diſſolutenes and looſeneſſe of life, in thy doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and behauiour, which doth offend both God and good men. and endeauour
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:150416:91"/> to be modeſt and ſettled in al thy geſtures.</p>
                  <p>Flie euill companies more then the plague, as euerie one likewiſe that shall giue thee naughtie counſel and bad example, and moreouer al occaſions and entiſements to ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Eſchewe aſſemblies, as carding, baunkets, daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, maskings, feaſts, vaine comedies &amp; other ſuch like thinges, by which God is highlie offended: and take heede that not onlie thou be not partaker of theſe
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:150416:92"/> things, but nether preſent at the dooing of them.</p>
                  <p>Beware of idlenes, as being a poiſon of the ſoule: &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to be alwaies buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, either in godlie works, or in ſuch as be profitable.</p>
                  <p>Be careful that in thy hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe there be no prophane booke, nor picture, much leſſe dishoneſt, neither on the walls, nor in bookes, nor in anie other things, becauſe it doth hurt thee, and is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue to others.</p>
                  <p>In traffique, ſelling and bying, flie all kinde of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:150416:92"/> falſehood, lying, &amp; oathes, &amp; deſiring of other mens goods.</p>
                  <p>Eſchewe, what lieth in thee to deale in other mens mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie or goods, vnles thou we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re bound by lawe of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or otherwiſe ſo to doe.</p>
                  <p>Neither for gayne, nor frindshippe, nor loue of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, nor fauour, muſt thou doe any thing that is not juſt, &amp; according to the will of God.</p>
                  <p>In proſperitie thou muſt beware of too much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and comfort, which
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:150416:93"/> doth cauſe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe headlong, into the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries &amp; dangers of this life.</p>
                  <p>At that time therefore bee mindfull of the calamities and chaunges of theſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie and worldlie things, and ſo it shall be verie expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to reade then for this end, ſome booke treating of the contempt &amp; vanitie of thinges conteined in this world, in like ſorte as a moſt holy and learned man was wont to doe, who in time of his greateſt proſperities, was accuſtomed to reade the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:150416:93"/> of the Prophet Ieremie.</p>
                  <p>In time of aduerſities, doe thou not looſe harte &amp; cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, neither bee thou euer ſory, but rather reioice, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that this is the right way to heauen, and one of the beſt tokens, that a man can haue of his ſaluation, &amp; be mindfull in ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to reade ſome ſpirituall treatiſe of tribulations.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="184" facs="tcp:150416:94"/>
                     <head>PARTICVLAR ADVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: and firſt of the custodie of the harte, and of all our ſences.</head>
                     <p>MAke a ſtedfaſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe neuer to offend Almighty God, chiefely through anie mortall ſinne; but rather to endure what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer euil, yea death it ſelfe, and to flie as much as lieth in thee, euerie ſorte of ſinne althought it were but venial.</p>
                     <p>Be vigilant to keepe thy hart, that there e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter no wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thought into it, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:150416:94"/> this often with thy ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, and examining alſo often in that which thou doſt faile</p>
                     <p>When any diſordered paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or wicked thought doth riſe in thee, procure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte it euen in the begining; and doe not giue it place in thee, but caſt it off, to the end that afterward it drawe thee not to ſinne.</p>
                     <p>Haue thou likewiſe exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greate care of thine eyes, not eaſilie lifting them vp, nor looking ſtedfaſtlie vpon that, which thou maiſt not lawfullie deſire.</p>
                     <pb n="186" facs="tcp:150416:95"/>
                     <p>Refraine thy toung, ſpeake not whatſoeuer cometh to thy mouth.</p>
                     <p>Remember that we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually tempted and enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronned on euerie ſide with diuels, which expect onlie how to make vs fall, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt be alwaies vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our garde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>SECONDLIE OF CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion and Communion.</head>
                     <p>BE carefull at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thou make a good ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall confeſſion of all thy
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:150416:95"/> life, if yet thou haue neuer made it before, to the end that the ſame may ſerue for the begining and foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a good new life, which thou doſt now purpoſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eade.</p>
                     <p>Thou shalt make choiſe of a good and learned ghoſtlie father, to be the guide of thy ſoule, to whome thou muſt giue great credittte, &amp; conferre with him in all thy difficulties &amp; doubts, as alſo in all other affaires of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in which there may be any burden of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:150416:96"/> and ſuffer thy ſelfe to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led according to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel.</p>
                     <p>Goe often to confeſſion, for that the oftener thou goeſt, the better it is, and ſee thou goe either euerie eight dayes, or at the leaſt euerie monthe, and moreouer, in all the ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne feaſts through out the whole yeare.</p>
                     <p>Likewiſe thou shalt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the bleſſed Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and when thou canſt not communicate, doe not therefore leaue to confeſſe, that ſo thou maiſt obtaine the grace which is giuen by
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:150416:96"/> this Sacrament.</p>
                     <p>Take heede thou neuer goe to bedd in ſtate of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne, but rather goe to confeſſe the ſame ſooner the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> latter: and if thou canſt nor out of hand doe ſo, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour at the leaſt, to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and ſorrowe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile thy ſinne bitterlie, and with the firſt opportunitie confeſſe thy ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Euerie weeke doe ſome kinde of penance, as faſting diſciplining, weareing of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are cloth, lying on the gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>und, and ſuch like thinges,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:150416:97"/> but all this muſt bee with aduiſe &amp; leaue of thy ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Father.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>THIRDLIE OF prayer &amp; ſpirituall exerciſes.</head>
                     <p>HAVE in thy chamber ſome deuout picture of Chriſt, of our Ladie, or of ſome other Sainte, to whom thou doeſt beare moſt deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>Thou oughteſt to haue holy water in thy chamber, &amp; going to ſleepe, riſing in the morning, entring in, or going out or thy chamber,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:150416:97"/> to ſprinkle thy ſelfe with the ſame, againſt al the deceits of the diuell.</p>
                     <p>Beare particular deuotion and reuerence to thy Angel keeper.</p>
                     <p>Thou shalt haue one alſo, or more Saints for thine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocats, as for example that Saint, whoſe name was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee in Baptiſme, and thou shalt take in particular, the glorious Virgin MARY for thy protectrice and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to her eſpeciallie in all thy neceſſities.</p>
                     <p>If thou canſt reade, thou
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:150416:98"/> shalt ſaie the office of our Ladie at leaſt vpon feaſt-daies, if not euerie day els: but thy beades thou shalt ſaie euerie day, or as ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou haſt leaſure.</p>
                     <p>Neuer leaue thy praier, at leaſt that of the morning and euening, but by all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes, whither thou be in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of others thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in the Church, or of thoſe of thine owne familie, or in thy woorke houſe, or whereſoeuer els thou art, or wither thou be alone. And being alone vſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:150416:98"/> if thou knowe how to doe it, or els that time ſaye the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Penitentiall Pſalmes, or the Litanies, or the Roſarie, or ſome other vocall prayer.</p>
                     <p>Remember to praye not onlie for thy ſelfe, but for al degrees of perſons, &amp; chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for the exaltation of the holie Catholicke Church; for the Popes holines, for thine owne Paſtor, for all Bishops, for all Chriſtian Princes, and principallie for thy King our Lord, for his Magiſtrates and Officers, and for the ſoules of thoſe
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:150416:99"/> that be departed out of this world.</p>
                     <p>Thou muſt be verie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout to thoſe Saints that bee protectors of thy Citie and Dioceſſe, and obſerue their feaſts, vigilles, &amp; reliques, principallie vpon the daies of their ſolemnities, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſeruice.</p>
                     <p>Faile not to goe to al gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall proceſſions, or to ſuch as be particular, which be within the cittie,</p>
                     <p>Likewiſe thou shalt goe to all prayers of forty houers, finishing thy hower when it
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:150416:99"/> shall fall to thy turne, &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dooing more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leſſe.</p>
                     <p>When ſigne is giuen to carrie the bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the ſicke, thou muſt nor faile to accompanie the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me deuoutlie, bearing thy candel: &amp; thou muſt glorie, &amp; not be ashamed to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie thy Lord, the King of the vniuerſall world. And going on the waye, thou shalt praye for the ſicke to whom it is carried, &amp; yeeld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to God that he hath vouchſfed to make vs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſo great a benefite, as
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:150416:100"/> to leaue vs himſelfe in this moſt excellent Sacrament.</p>
                     <p>This office, to accompanie this moſt bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whither it muſt at any time be carried, thou shalt performe as often as thou shalt meete it on the waie, lighting, downe alſo from thy coache or chariot, if thou were in it.</p>
                     <p>When it ringeth to the Aue Maria in the morning, at noone, and at euening, thou shait ſaie three times the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue Maria on thy knees, and alſo thoſe three verſes, which
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:150416:100"/> are ſett downe in the dailie exerciſe, printed in the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of our Ladie, calling to minde, the Incarnation and Paſſion of our Lord IESVS CHRIST.</p>
                     <p>When at home, or in any other place, thou shalt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the belle tole at the eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Sauiour in the high Maſſe, thou muſt be mindfull of the lifting vp of thy Redeemer on the Croſſe, &amp; kneeling downe lift vp thy mind to adore and worship him, and make a short praier vnto him, as
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:150416:101"/> if he were preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before thee</p>
                     <p>As often as they ring for any one that is dead, thou muſt praie for him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er that thou art th fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him shortlie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore purpoſe with thy ſelfe to be in a readines.</p>
                     <p>When they ring againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt, beſides that thou muſt ſpeedilie moue thy ſelf to prayer for that daunger, going in haſt to the Church or els performing the ſame in the place where thou, art at that preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thou oughteſt alſo to thinke vpon thoſe
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:150416:101"/> thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, lightnings &amp; feares that shall be on that day, when Chriſt shall come to iudge the vniuerſall world.</p>
                     <p>Accuſtome thy ſelfe, to thoſe kind of prayers which the Saints doe call Iaculato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſaying often in the day with thy hart or mouth (but yet verie ſoftlie, when thou art in preſence of others) ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me breefe ſentence out of the Pſalms, or other place of holy ſcripture, or els short prayers that may lighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, &amp; reuiue thy affection towardes God in
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:150416:102"/> euerie occaſion that doth preſent it ſelfe: as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple; in the begining of euerie thing. <hi>Deus in adiutorium me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um intende. Domine ad adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uandum me feſtina:</hi> In thy dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, <hi>In te Domine ſperaui non confundar in aeternum;</hi> In thy afflictions. <hi>Saluum me fac Domine, quoniam intrauerunt aquae, vſque ad animam meam:</hi> In thy temptations, <hi>Adiutor meus eſto, ne derelinquas me:</hi> In conſidering thy owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: <hi>Miſerere mei Domine, quoniam infirmus ſum:</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring thine owne ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:150416:102"/> 
                        <hi>Sana me Domine &amp; ſana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor:</hi> Deſiring to loue our Lord, <hi>Diligam te Domine for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo mea;</hi> In al thy doubts, <hi>Deus meus illumina, tenebras meas.</hi> Wishing perſeuerance to do good, <hi>Deus meus es tu, ne diſceſſeris à me;</hi> and ſuch like praiers, of which the Pſalmes, and other bookes of holy ſcripture, &amp; the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liloquies or ghoſtly aſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Saints are full, as thou maiſt learne of thy ghoſtly father.</p>
                     <p>In the night time when thou doſt awake, and canſt
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:150416:103"/> not ſleepe, let thy minde be occupied in God and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall thinges, neither doe thou giue place to any fleashly thoughts, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay ſome pſalmes, or thy beades, with deuotion.</p>
                     <p>When thou goeſt to bed, thinke that perhaps thou shalt not be aliue in the morning: and when thou doſt ariſe in the morning, that peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture thou shalt not liue till night, &amp; ſo thou wilt looke well to thy ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Trafficking or labouring, endeuoure to occupie thy
<pb facs="tcp:150416:103"/> minde on ſome ſpirituall thing, as in that which our Sauiour Chriſt, or any Saint did or thought, or in ſinging Pſalmes or ſpirituall ſonges.</p>
                     <p>Euery time that thou doſt goe or returne from doing any thing, eſteeme that thy Angell keeper is in thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie, &amp; readie to help thee, counting al thy prayers and good workes: and thinke that thou art in the preſence of our Sauiour Chriſt, and in his companie.</p>
                     <p>Studie to drawe ſome fruite and spirituall meaning of
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:150416:104"/> euerie thinge that is done, that happeneth, or thou ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte: As for tilling the groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, with what trauaile and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it is requiſite to till our ſoule that it may render good fruite to our Lord? Of a faire ſunne shining daie, what pleaſure it wil bee to ſee that eternall light of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſith this other doth ſo much delight vs? Of an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and cloudie day, what a torment shal it be, to dwel for euer in eternall darknes, ſeeing that a littell miſtie water, doth ſo much diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:150416:104"/> thee? And of a garden full of odoriferous &amp; ſweete flowers; how goodlie a thing it is, and how much God is delighted in a ſoule adorned with flowers, that haue ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie colours of vertues; and how paſſing great the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of almightie God is, for ſo much as we ſee ſ ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent arte and skill in a flower, or in one onlie leafe? and the like thou maiſt doe in all other creatures.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="206" facs="tcp:150416:105"/>
                     <head>FOVRTHLY OF THE particular exerciſe in the morning.</head>
                     <p>IN the morning whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doſt riſe, firſt of all other thinges haue recourſe to God, requeſting him of his helpe, &amp; betake thy ſelfe to prayer, before thou occupie thy mind in any other thing &amp; amongſt the reſt of thy deuout prayers, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in particular to ſaie the, <hi>Pater noſter, Aue Maria,</hi> and <hi>Creede.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So ſoone as thou doſt
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:150416:105"/> awake occupie thy mind in God, and thinke that euen then thy Angell doth call thee, that thou goe with him to praiſe our Lord.</p>
                     <p>In putting on thy apparell, thinke vpon ſome ſpirituall thinge. As for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, how in baptiſme thou waſt clothed with grace, &amp; that thou art a pilgrime, &amp; doſt goe towards the countrie of heauen.</p>
                     <p>After this kneeling downe in the place appointed for praier, firſt of al tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke God, that he hath preſerued thee that night, &amp; kept thee till
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:150416:106"/> this time, and doth beſtowe ſo many benefits vpon thee.</p>
                     <p>Then pray him that he will defend thee that daie &amp; euer from all ſinne, and that thou offend him not at any time.</p>
                     <p>That he giue thee grace to fulfill alwaies his holy will, and to direct all thinges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording, to his beſt pleaſure.</p>
                     <p>Offer vp thy ſelf vnto him, &amp; all that which thou art to doe, ſay, or thinke, with a pure intention, that al may be to his praiſe and gloire.</p>
                     <p>Commend thy ſelfe to the
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:150416:106"/> moſt glorius Virgin, and to thine Angell keeper, to thy Saint protector, and to all Saints, ſaying ſome good prayer to this intent.</p>
                     <p>Afterwards for ſome ſpace of time make thy mental or vocall prayer, according to the commmoditie and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie which thou haſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>FIFTHLY OF THE praier &amp; exerciſe to be made at euening before thou lie downe to ſleepe.</head>
                     <p>AT euening after ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or at ſome other
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:150416:107"/> time: reade, if thou be able a little of ſome deuout and ſpirituall booke, or of the Saints liues, or ſuch like, and chieflie of the S. whoſe daie that is, thinking for ſome short ſpace vpon the ſame,</p>
                     <p>Before thou goe to ſleepe. kneeling downe before ſome holie Image, firſt giue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to God for his benefits receaued in generall, and ſpeciallie that daie, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al demaunde grace and true light, to knowe and hate which is ſinne; then next examen thy conſcience of
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:150416:107"/> whatſoeuer thou haſt do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, ſaide, or thought that daie, and requeſt his diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to pardonne all the faultes and offences thou shalt find in thy ſelfe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſtedfaſt purpoſe, with Gods helpe and aſſiſtance, to be more warie in time to come, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe thee, with the firſt opportunitie of what is paſt.</p>
                     <p>In putting off thy apparel, thinke that for ſinne man was bereaued of grace, and that it is needeful that we caſt off our euil habits and
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:150416:108"/> inclinations; or els think of ſome other good thing, or ſaie ſome deuout prayer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>SIXTLY OF THE manner how to pray and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a mans ſelfe in the Church</head>
                     <p>ENdeauour thy ſelfe to make thy prayers kneeling and with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt deuotion thou canſt.</p>
                     <p>Going to the place of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, conſider that our Lord is there preſent to behould what thou doſt, &amp; whither thou doe it as thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</p>
                     <p>Hearing the peale to
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:150416:108"/> Maſſe, or to the reſt of the diuine ſeruice to which thou art to goe, lift vp thy mind to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that thou arte to goe to pray and to aſſiſt, at the oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Sacrifice of the bodie and bloud of our sauiour Chiſt IESVS, for the remiſſion of thy ſinnes, or els to praiſe God. And therefore thou muſt goe with greate contrition and deuotion.</p>
                     <p>Entering into the Church, when thou doſt take holy water, lifte vp thy ſoule, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that thou art bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:150416:109"/> and what thou dideſt promiſe there at, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to wash thy ſoule from ſinne with teares, and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, purpoſing to lead a newe life hence forward.</p>
                     <p>In the Church behaue thy ſelfe with reuerence and feare of God, ſtanding in thy place, not in that of the Clergie, or appointed for anie other ſtate of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do thou, ſit vnreuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with thy backe towades the bleſſed Sacrament, nor approach not to the foote, nor within the railes of the
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:150416:109"/> Altars, and eſchew, being in the Church, whatſoeuer ſpeach, motion, geſture or acte, that may be thought irreuerent or vndecent.</p>
                     <p>Be attentiue to the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſeruice, and looke not to any other thing, but to thoſe moſt holy myſteries, and ſuch things as haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion.</p>
                     <p>At Maſſe be alwaies kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and at the Ghoſpell ſtand vp right.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="216" facs="tcp:150416:110"/>
                     <head>SEVENTHLY OF exerciſes to be done vpon holie daies, and other bleſſed times and Vigills.</head>
                     <p>BE carefull to ſpend the holy daies, not in vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but in good workes.</p>
                     <p>Procure vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feaſt-daies to heare Maſſe in thine owne parish-Church, and there to harken to ſuch good leſſons as be giuen thee, and vſe what diligence thou canſt, to be inſtructed in thoſe thinges, which euerie chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is bound to know for his ſaluation, and be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:150416:110"/> to vſe, the good ould cuſtome of offering at Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe time.</p>
                     <p>Endeauour vpon feaſt-daies, to heare Euen ſong &amp; diuine ſeruice.</p>
                     <p>Endeauour to heare ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons &amp; holy leſſons, not only vpon holy daies, but vpon all other dayes, when thou canſt haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; this not for curioſitie, but to take fruite thereby, going there to heare them, where thou doeſt finde moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward feeling: procuring alſo with greate diligence to put
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:150416:111"/> them in practiſe.</p>
                     <p>When any feaſt or ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of holy time is neere, as of Adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, of Sexageſima, of Lent, &amp; the like, ſee that thou renewe thy whole life and manners, preparing thy ſelfe to celebrate the ſame, with Confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, and ſuch other godlie exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes.</p>
                     <p>In euerie Sunday of Adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to doe that which a holy Bishop doth warne thee of, that is, to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with great deuotion and pureneſſe: and the like
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:150416:111"/> thou muſt procure to doe vpon the Sundaies of Lent,</p>
                     <p>Vpon faſting-daies, thou muſt acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany thy faſting with often prayer, and alſo with almeſ-deeds, if thou be able.</p>
                     <p>Albeit thou eate but one meale vpon faſting-daies, yet, as S. Auſtine doth warne thee, thou muſt not loade thy table with too great ſtore of meate,</p>
                     <p>That which thou doeſt ſaue in ſuch daies, and not ſpend in ſupper, it shall be very good to giue to the
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:150416:112"/> poore for Gods ſake.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>EIGHTLY OF GOOD and godlie workes</head>
                     <p>TAke delight in the workes of mercie, to doe almes, to viſite the hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalles, thoſe that be in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or ſick folkes, and by all meanes that thou maiſt to helpe the poore, chiefelie thoſe that be in neceſſitie.</p>
                     <p>Seeke to be of ſome holy congregation or company, of godly &amp; vertuous men, ſo to do ſome good work &amp; occupie thy ſelfe well, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:150416:112"/> vpon feaſt daies.</p>
                     <p>Be readie with that littell or much, that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee of worldly ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce &amp; where thou doeſt wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this with thy owne labour and ſweate, to helpe the Churches, and ſpecially thy parish where thine owne church is, for the orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and other neceſſities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that all things bee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with ſuch decencie, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the houſe of God.</p>
                     <p>When thou doeſt ſee thy neighbour to bee in any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſinne, or ready to fall,
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:150416:113"/> vſe towards him thy dutiful brotherlie correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or warning with charitie &amp; diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thereby to gaine him.</p>
                     <p>Such as be noble, riche, men of high degree, &amp; Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors, muſt be as it were guides and examples, to others of lower calling, in all ſort of godly and pious workes.</p>
                     <p>If thou feele thy ſelfe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to goe any holy pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, take aduiſe of thy ghoſtly Father, and omitt not in any wiſe to haue his benediction, according to
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:150416:113"/> the auncient vſe of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church.</p>
                     <p>If thou goe any voyage, vſe euerie morning, ere thou goe on thy way, to ſay thoſe briefe &amp; short prayers which are called <hi>Itinerariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or iournal, and be printed in the office of our Ladie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>NINTHLY OF MEATE, drinke and apparell.</head>
                     <p>EVery time that thou doſt goe to the table to eate, thou muſt thinke that thou doſt goe for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, ſake, &amp; ſay firſt the
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:150416:114"/> benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that is in our Ladies office, &amp; often giue thanks to our Lord, as is there alſo conteined: &amp; if thou canſt not ſay theſe things, ſay a <hi>Pater noster,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> making the ſigne of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Croſſe vpon the table, &amp; meate.</p>
                     <p>When thou doſt ſit downe or art at the table, think firſt of al before thou begin to eate, vpon that ſinne which our firſt parents did comitt, by eating the forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: for this will ſerue as a bridel to refraine thine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:150416:114"/> &amp; as a rule whereby to meaſure that action of thine.</p>
                     <p>Endeauour to be verie te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, in eating, &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſleeping, &amp; clothing, in clining rather to too litle, then to too much.</p>
                     <p>Beware of pompe &amp; pride of apparel, &amp; of all ſorte of vaine, &amp; ſuperfluous dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king &amp; triming: haue greate regarde vnto this, whether thou be a man or a woman, or of whatſoeuer els condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; degree.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb n="226" facs="tcp:150416:115"/>
                  <pb n="227" facs="tcp:150416:115"/>
                  <p>A BRIEFE AND PROFITABLE EXERCISE.</p>
                  <p>OF THE SEAVEN PRINCIPALL EFFV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the pretious blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>WHEREWITH <hi>VVe may exerciſe our ſelues all the dayes in the weeke in one of theſe ſeauen Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, And to obtaine the ſeauen vertues contrary to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd vices.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TRANSLATED Out of the French into Engliſh, by IOHN HEIGHAM.</p>
                  <p>At. s. Omers, Anno 1624.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <pb n="228" facs="tcp:150416:116"/>
                  <pb n="229" facs="tcp:150416:116"/>
                  <head>THE FIRSTE Effuſion on Sonday.</head>
                  <p>FIRSTE vpon the Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, we are to haue in memorie the firſte Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour IESVS, the which was in the garden of Oliuet. In this day ought the denout ſoule to enter into this gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, &amp; to contemplate as if he were preſent in ſpirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlding how the bleſſed
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:150416:117"/> Sonne of God was there in maruelous ſorrowe &amp;c ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to redeeme vs, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and in gratefull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the goulfe of hell, he was abandonned, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued, of all comfort, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe and ſuccour: of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie Father, of his Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les which lay a ſleep, of his neighbors, and kinsfolkes, and of all his frendes &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance. Wherefore he had iuſt cauſe to ſay, <hi>My ſoule is ſorrowfull euen vnto death.</hi> And as the Prophet Dauid ſaith: <hi>My frendes &amp;
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:150416:117"/> my Neighbours haue approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and stoode against me, and they that were neere me, ſtoode far off.</hi> To witt, the chiefe Prieſtes, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Doctours, to whom of loue, he had shewed &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſo many workes for their good and benefit, and for whoſe ſakes eſpecially he was come into this world.</p>
                  <p>And ſeeing furthermore, that the merit of his dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, should nothing profitte the greateſt part of the world, as the ſcripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith. <hi>Many be called, but few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ect</hi> (albeit that one only
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:150416:118"/> of his pretious bloode was ſufficient alone to ſaue the whole worlde) by this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and by the greate deſire which he had to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish our redemption, and to make ſatisfaction for our ſinnes, and to ſaue vs, he apprehended ſuch an ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and exceſſiue ſorro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we, that there iſſued out of al partes of his bodie, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſweate conuerted into bloode, which peirced through his garments and ran vpon the earth. Then might he well ſay
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:150416:118"/> with the holie Prophet, <hi>My ſoule is replenished wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> euills.</hi> And as Elias meaſured him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe three times vpon the dead infant, ſaying. O Lord I beſeeche thee, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſoule of this Infant may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe into him: ſo our Sauiour and redeemer IESVS, proſtrated him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe three times vpon the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arth, praying deuoutlie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Father, to reuiue ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſoules which were dead by ſinne:</p>
                  <p>And then the deuout ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ought to approach, and
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:150416:119"/> to ioyne him to IESVS CHRIST proſtrat vpon the ground, and by amourouſe compaſsion to lift him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, and to gather vp the droppes of his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood, and to poure them into the violl of his harte, ſaying deuoutlie the prayer which followeth.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The prayer for the firſt Effuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Salute the moſt noble &amp; pretious blood runing in greate aboundance out of the bodie of my Lord and Sauiour IESVS, being in
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:150416:119"/> the garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of oliuet in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: repleate with maruellous and exceſsiue agonie, by the conſideration of his moſt bitter and shamefull paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo neere approaching; which he was to ſuffer, for the ſatisfaction of all the offences and ſinnes, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated &amp; committed from the beginning of the world, &amp; which euer shalll be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, to the latter ending of the ſame.</p>
                     <p>O moſt ſweete IESVS, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>umblie, I beſeeche thee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat by the vertue of this
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:150416:120"/> bleſſed bloodie ſweate, thou wouldeſt cleanſe and purge my poore ſoule, defiled with diuerſe ſortes of ſinnes, which I haue often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſlouth, ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, negligence, omiſſion, faintnes of heart, ſinnes of my youth, and perdition of the pretious time in idlenes by thoughtes, wordes, and worldly occupations. that I may conforme my ſelfe to the wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ſaieth: <hi>He which tilleth his lande shall be filled with breads: but he which purſueth idlenes, is a very foole</hi>
                        <pb n="237" facs="tcp:150416:120"/> wherefore I should be moſt foolish and vnwiſe, if now I should no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> laboure by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of my life, to gather vp the droppes of thy moſt precious blood, which thou haſt shed for my redemption.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore, ſweete IESV, I humblie beſeeche thee, by the vertue of thy ſacred blood, shed in the garden of Oliuet, thorough ardent lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, that it may pleaſe thee to giue me the vertu of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and the feruor of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion: illuminate my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:150416:121"/> &amp; inflame my affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the loue of thee: that for the time to come, I may dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlie, attentiuelie, &amp; deuoutlie, be vigilant, &amp; watchfull in Prayer, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Maſſe, in ſaying my houres, or other diuine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and vertuous operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: fruitefullie alſo to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploie my time, in workes of pietie, pittie, and mercie, to thy honour, and glorie, to my ſaluation, and edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my neighbour.</p>
                     <p>True it is, o my Lord, that full often doeſt thou enſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:150416:121"/> me, often to call vpon thee, and dooſt further inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te me, by promiſing to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re me, ſaying. <hi>All thinges whatſoeuer you shall aske in prayer beleuing, you shal recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue.</hi> Wherefore hereafter I wil be more diligent, by the helpe of thy grace, the which for this purpoſe, I will euer ſeeke and require, vntill I may attaine.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore, my ſweete Sauiour IESVS, for the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſorrowe, anguishe &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy bleſſed hart, for all thy ſighes, groanes,
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:150416:122"/> and droppes of bloodie te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ares shed in this garden. I adore thee, loue thee, and laude thee, beſeeching thee by thy exceſsiue ſorrowe, and aboundant effuſion of thy precious blood, to dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vtterly from my hart, all foolishe, and worldlie vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, mirthe, ioy and diſordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate paſtimes, that I may be wholie eſtranged from al ſuch vanities, &amp; to ſay with the Prophet. <hi>Turne away myne eyes, Lord, leaſt they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould &amp; looke after vanities:</hi> And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort me, I beſeeche
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:150416:122"/> thee, in all my tribulations, as thou haſte promiſed me, ſaying; <hi>I am with him in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation: I wil deliuer him, and wil glorifie him.</hi> Giue me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo true and holie Compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and teares of Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of loue, the which I deſire with the Prophet, ſaying: <hi>Who shall giue vnto myne eyes a fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of teares, that I may weepe both day and night.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O ſweete IESVS, lett the continuall memorie of thy dolorous Paſſion, wholie ſwallow me vp in the zeale,
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:150416:123"/> and ardour of thy loue, and ſuch zeale as thou hadeſt of thy Fathers houſe, ſuch zeale lett there be in my ſoule towardes thee, that I may not think but of thee, and euer to repoſe by grace and loue, wholie in thee, Amen. <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <head>THE SECONDE Effuſion on Monday.</head>
                  <p>SEcondlie on Monday, we muſt conſider and contemplat, how foure Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, voide of all pittie, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiled
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:150416:123"/> our Sauiour IESVS. And how theſe foure mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, cruell as Lions, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>und him ſtreightlie, and will anouſlie to the Piller, and as foure greedie wolues, hongring, &amp; thirſting for the blood of this innocent lambe, moſt inhumanly ſtripped him, beate him, ſcourged him, wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him, and tore his tender and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall flesh, with thornie roddes, ſcorpio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of iron, in ſuch ſort that there was no whole parte in all his bodie, wherefore
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:150416:124"/> rightlie might he ſay. <hi>They haue ſtroken me, and wounded me,</hi> ſo that from the ſole of my foote, to the crowne of my head, there was no whole place in me.</p>
                  <p>And then the deuout ſoule, ought with teares and ſobbes to ſay. He hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forme nor beautie left him, for blood which pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth downe on euery ſide, and his body altogether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured: we haue ſeene him as hauing no ſighte, and his face all beſpitt and defiled: we haue eſteemed him as a
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:150416:124"/> Leaper, ſmitten of God and humbled: but he it is who is wounded for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and peirced for our ſinnes. The figure hereof was the good Iob, who was ſtroken full of vlcers and ſoares, from the ſole of the foote to the top of his head. And in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner was our bleſſed Sauiour in his fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellation, which the good Chriſtian conſidering, he may make his praier ſaying</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The prayer for the <hi>2.</hi> Effuſion.</head>
                     <p>I Salute the moſt worthie, and pretious blood,
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:150416:125"/> which ranne in great abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance out of the noble bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of my redemer and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour IESVS, being moſt hardlie bound to the Piller, and moſt cruellie beaten, and ſcourged, in ſuch lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table wiſe, that al his ſacred body was ful of woundes, and no parte remayned en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſole of his foote, to the crowne of his head.</p>
                     <p>O moſt patient IESVS, I beſeeche thee, that by the vertu of thy moſt holie blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, powred out in ſuch gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at aboundance, and ſoiled,
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:150416:125"/> &amp; fowled vnder the feete of thoſe fellons, tirants, and murderers, and by thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable meekenes, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, vouchſafe to pardon me all my ſinnes, and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, which I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thorough ire, mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, rancour, impatience, periurie, blaſphemie, iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, contumelie, reproache, opprobrie, indignation, and deſire of vengeance, by the which I haue full often haynouſlie offended thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine majeſtie. And moſt hartelie I beſeeche thee, O
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:150416:126"/> my Sauiour, to giue vnto me, the vertu of ſweetnes, benignity, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetude, mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, ſupportation, tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and perfect patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: to the end that I may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hereafter, more aima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, peaceable, ſweete, affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, beninge, and gentle to all perſons, as thy bleſſed Apoſtle S. Paule cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelleth, ſaying. <hi>Beare yee one an others burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſo you shal fulfill the lawe of Chriſt.</hi> And that ſo I may be a faithfull obſeruer of the lawe of my ſweete Lord IESVS CHRIST.</p>
                     <pb n="249" facs="tcp:150416:126"/>
                     <p>O moſt bening Sauiour, and redeemer, I adore, lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and giue thee thankes, for the great shame which thou ſuffredſt, being naked before all the world, and for that thou wouldeſt be moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for the shame of my ſinnes: giue me grace, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche thee, clearely, and entirelie, to declare all my ſinnes in Confeſſion, and not to appeare before thee at the hower of my death, naked of vertues, merits and good workes. And I render thee hartie thankes,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:150416:127"/> for all the dolours, which thou ſuffredſt in thy hard flagellation, and for all thy droppes of blood which thou haſt shed for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of my ſinnes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thy goodnes, from the bottom of my harte, by the merits of thy bitter ſcourging, of al thy wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and effuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thy pretious blood, at the houre of my death, to deliuer me from all ſinne and paines, that being all pure and cleane, purged and washed from all ſpots of ſinne, I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:150416:127"/> out of this preſent life, into euerlaſting glorie there to laude, and glorifie thee for euer.</p>
                     <p>I beſeeche thee alſo, ſweete IESV, that to conforme me to thy dolorous Paſſion, I may for the loue of thee, tollerate, and beare patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and in humilite of hart, without murmuring, or contradiction, all iniurie, deriſion, confuſion, villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, detraction, perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and generallie all aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and tribulation, and thy Fatherly correction, ſuch
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:150416:128"/> as thou shalt pleaſe to ſend me; and alwaies for the ſame, without end to laude thee, and to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der thee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual thankes and praiſes. Amen. <hi>Pater noster, Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <head>THE THIRDE Effuſion on Tueſday.</head>
                  <p>THIRDLIE on Tueſday, we ought to thinke and meditate, how the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sonne of God, was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiered with a veſtment, or purple mantell, and how
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:150416:128"/> thoſe fellons, and cruell butchers, impoſed vpon his holie and reuerend head (which is the honour of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, the mirrour of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the patterne of all beautie) a ſharpe Crowne of Thornes, verie peirce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſmitting thereon with ſtaues, to enforce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with violence, to peirce his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable head, ſo that the thornes did paſſe into his braines, wherwith his clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and beautifull face was al bloodie, and on euerie ſide goared, and they afterwards
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:150416:129"/> impudently, ſpitt in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſage, and mocked him, in ſo much that he was made the moſt deformed, and disfigured, that euer was beheld.</p>
                  <p>To conforme himſelfe to this article, and to redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce into memorie, this third Effuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacred blood of our Lord and Sauiour, call to minde theſe figures: how Sampſon was mocked of the Philiſtians, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Note alſo, ſleeping in his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle vncouered, was mock<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:150416:129"/> of his ſonne, &amp; for this was accurſed of his Father. Elizeus was derided of the little children, ſaying. Goe vp bald-head; and for this deriſion they were curſed of him, and torne in peeces by two wilde Beares. And by theſe perſonages, which were ſo mocked, is ſignified our Lord, who was alſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cked of his enimies in his paſſion. We may likewiſe call to minde, that which is written in the Canticles: ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ying Goe forth thou daug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hter of Sion, &amp; behold the
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:150416:130"/> King Salomon with his crowne, where-with his mother (that is the Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of the Iewes) hath crowned him in the day of his eſpouſales. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuout ſoule may ſay, in great bitternes, &amp; profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de humilitie, as followeth.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The prayer for the third Effuſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Salute the moſt noble, and pretious blood, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning downe aboundantlie, from the bleſſed &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d head, of my Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour IESVS CHRIST, to wash
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:150416:130"/> and purge my ſoule from all my ſinnes. O moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; moſt patient Sonne of God, King of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and of earth, my God, and my Creator, humblie I adore thee, and glorifie thee. For me thou haſt e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dured many mockeries, iniuries, and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, being cloathed with a purple mantell, crowned with a crowne of moſt pricking thornes, holding in thy hand (inſtead of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Scepter) a light, and rotten Reede. Alas my moſt element and meeke Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:150416:131"/> IESV, how much paine and torment haſt thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for me in thy bleſſed head. Alas my God &amp; deere ſpouſe of my ſoule, it is my ſinne that hath cauſed thee this maruellous dolour and afflictions.</p>
                     <p>O good IESV, for the great torment, dolour, vituperie, deriſion, opprobrie, &amp; effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy moſt pretious blood, in this agonion, I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore thee, and thanke thee, for thy profounde humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and infinite goodnes in the merit of this effuſion:
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:150416:131"/> humbly beſeeching thee, that thou wilt pardon al my ſinnes, which I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thoroughe pride, preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, arrogancie, vaine glorie, oſtentation, diſordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate appetit of honors, po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, worldlie glorie, eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my ſelfe, diſobedience to others, and all other bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Pride, to the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (after the councel of Saint Paule) I eſteeme not too much of my ſelfe; <hi>Be not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>wiſe in your owne conceite, but feare</hi> by the which feare I may (by thy grace) obtaine the
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:150416:132"/> noble vertu of humilitie, which is the foundation, &amp; garde of all other vertues: and that I may euer thinke humblie of my ſelfe, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne all worldlie honors, and vaine glorie, and euer deſire to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed, and counted moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte, ſaying with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. <hi>I reioyce in myne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O ſweete IESVS, giue me from henceforth, a hart co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, humble, and obedient to thy holie commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Giue me a hart ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:150416:132"/> to thine owne hart, which may be tranſperced with ſuch ardent charitie, &amp; cordiall compaſſion, that I may be alwayes mindefull of thee, ſtudie to pleaſe thee, euer to repoſe in thee, &amp; neuer to be ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee. Amen. <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <head>THE FOVRTHE Effuſion on VVenſday.</head>
                  <p>FOVRTHLY on wenſday, we ought to call to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, and to meditate, how our Lord and Sauiour IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS,
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:150416:133"/> was led forth of the Cittie of Hieruſalem, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius Theeues, towardes, the mount of Caluarie, bearing vpon his shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a heauie, and waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Croſſe, of fifteene foote longe, which put him to maruellous paine and trauell, and cauſed a verie great and greeuous wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, in his ſacred shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: in ſo much that the blood ranne abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantlie downe the midle of his back: &amp; ſo was he led, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:150416:133"/> &amp; pushed forward, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rudely, &amp; forcebly, with great shame, wearines, &amp; paine, vnto the mount of Caluarie to be crucified.</p>
                  <p>In figure hereof, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tooke the wood of the ſacrifice, &amp; laid it vpon the shoulders of Iſaac his ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, to offer him vp to God. And our Sauiour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to the end of his way, vpon this hil of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaire, there was preſented vnto him (to refresh and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort him) moſt bitter gaul &amp; vineger, as the Prophet
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:150416:134"/> foretold ſaying. <hi>In my thirste, they gaue me vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to drinke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The deuout ſoule, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme him ſelfe to this article, ought to goe forth of the eſtate of all ſinnes and vices, by an earneſt deteſtation of them, and vtterlie abandoning this wicked, vnhappie, and wretched world: and with hartie contrition and repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for his ſinnes, in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of ſoule, and grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> compaſſion, ought he to goe alonge with his Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150416:134"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150416:135"/>
                     <pb n="265" facs="tcp:150416:135"/> God, and with the dolorous Virgin Marie, and helpe him carry his croſſe, and to gather vp the drops of his pretious blood, which ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne from his ſacred shoulders, and from his whole body, ſorely bruſed and wounded, thorough the great trauaile and payne which he ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in this hard &amp; oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious voyage, in ſo much that he fel on the earth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Croſſe, thorough great weaknes, debility, &amp; faintnes, being in a manner halfe dead. Wherefore that
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:150416:136"/> we may be partakers of the merits of the ſame bleſſed paſſion of our Sauiour IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS Chriſt, let vs ſay de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly this prayer follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The prayer for the fourth Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</head>
                     <p>I Salute the moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood of my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer IESVS, the which he ſhed forth going towardes the mount of Caluary, to receaue that moſt cruel and ſhameful death for my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, bearing that heauy
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:150416:136"/> Croſſe vpon his ſhoulders, ſo pittifully torne, bruſed &amp; wounded: which Croſſe was ſo great, and weighty, that the Sonne of God fell to the ground vnder it.</p>
                     <p>O my ſoule goe thou by the ſide of thy ſweet louer, and Lord, &amp; behould how for the loue of thee, he is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercharged with this pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Croſſe, hauing laide all thy ſins vpon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to carry them to the mount of Caluary, to faſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and nayle them to his holy Croſſe, &amp; to reconcile thee
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:150416:137"/> in his blood, to his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father.</p>
                     <p>Behould, O my ſoule, how thy Sauiour IESVS, by the burthen of his croſſe, and great feeblenes, by the debility of his body, ſo far ſpent, and ouerwearyed, is not able to go any further, but with exceeding payne, and dolour. Haue then pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and compaſſion on him, in all his paynes, agonyes, and calamityes, and aſſiſte him to beare &amp; ſupport his Croſſe, by bearing thy own croſſe of pennance, and of
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:150416:137"/> all tribulation, and aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, voluntarily, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, for the loue of him, ſaying:</p>
                     <p>O moſt ſweet Ieſus, who wouldeſt beare thy Croſſe in great doulour and payne with ſo many improperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, illuſions, and diriſions of thyne enemies; humbly I beſeech thee, that by the ſame ſufferance, dolour and trauaile, which thou ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt in bearing of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy Croſſe, to giue me gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in this preſent life, glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to beare my croſſe of pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:150416:138"/> and of all ſufferan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that I may neuer be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from thee, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and meekely in all patience, to follow thee to the death, and with thee to dye vpon the croſſe, full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling thy holy councell, ſaying: <hi>If any man will come after me, let him take vp his Croſſe dayly and follow me.</hi> And againe: <hi>He that doth not beare his Croſſe, and come after me, cannot be my diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O deere IESV, I beſeech thee, by the drinke &amp; bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:150416:138"/> liquor, which in greate malice was giuen to thee on the mount of caluary, for comfort and refreſhing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy labour and hard tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, that thou wouldeſt pardon all my offences, which I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by the ſinne of Gluttony. For well I know it to be thy wil, not only by thy owne holy example, but alſo by the doctrine of thy bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle which admoniſheth vs, <hi>That we walke honeſtly and vertuouſly, not in gorma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſing and wantones.</hi> And in
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:150416:139"/> another place he ſayth: <hi>I chaſtice my body and bring it into ſeruitude.</hi> Which I alas, haue euelly obſerued, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in drinking, &amp; eating, ſuch exquiſite and delicate diſhes; in multitude, &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of viandes, and dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable licours: in violating, and breaking the faſting-dayes commaunded, and dayes of abſtinence.</p>
                     <p>Wherfore giue me good Lord, the vertue of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſobriety, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, both in my eating and drinking, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:150416:139"/> to haue a holy mean and meaſure, both in the quantity, &amp; quality, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may hould in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, my body, and ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to the ſpirit &amp; reaſon: and to be more vigilant in prayer, meditation, and contemplation, of ſpiritual, diuine, &amp; heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thinges, and other vertuous and profitable indeuours: and to be ſo much more diligent and feruent, deuoutlie &amp; reuerently to accomplishe thy diuine ſeruice, to loue, honor, and laude thee for
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:150416:140"/> euer more, Amen. <hi>Pater noster. Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <head>THE FIFTH EF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion on Thurſday.</head>
                  <p>FIFTHLY, we ought to haue in minde &amp; thinke, how the bleſſed Sonne of God, being arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the mount of calua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, much trauailed, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and exceeding feeble, was by thoſe fellons, &amp; murderers, rudelie and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly deſpoiled, whereby all his former woundes were renewed, &amp; began to bleed
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:150416:140"/> a freshe, by reaſon that his coate cleaued faſt vnto his bleſſed body, the which was a maruellous paine and torment vnto him, for in this violent extraction of his robe, the blood ran downe a new, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all partes of his bleſſed bodie.</p>
                  <p>The figure hereof was shewed, when Ioſeph was deſpoiled by his bretheren, and his coate dipped in the blood of a kidde. To com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe to this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle the deuout ſoule ought to ſay this prayer following.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="276" facs="tcp:150416:141"/>
                     <head>The prayer for the fifthe Effuſion.</head>
                     <p>I Salute the moſt pretious blood of my Sauiour IESVS, shed forth aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantlie on the mount of Caluarie, by the rude, and violent extraction of his coate, which held and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo faſt vnto him, that all his pretious woundes were renewed, &amp; the blood dropped downe from his bleſſed bodie vpon the grounde.</p>
                     <p>I beſeech thee, moſt ſweete
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:150416:141"/> IESVS, for that willinglie &amp; voluntarilie, thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be vncloathed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiled nakedly before all the world, ſuffering, great shame and confuſion for the shame and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of myne offences, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riche me, wouldeſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of all kind of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes, make me to be inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relie diſpoiled of all kinde of wordlie contentments, ſo farr as they are ether co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, or hurtfull to my ſaluation, to the end that in all nakednes, I may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:150416:142"/> thee, nakedlie crucified on the croſſe.</p>
                     <p>And pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, I beſeeche thee, all my ſinnes &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, which I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in my apparell, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, and habits of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluitie, and in my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in all other thinges exceeding myne eſtate, that I may ſay with Saint Paule. <hi>I haue made all thinges as detriment, and doe eſteeme them as doung, that I may gayne Christ.</hi> And lett me not appeare naked of al vertues, merittes, and good
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:150416:142"/> workes, before thee, at the houre of my death, and dreadfull day of iudgment. And by the vertue and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of thy moſt noble &amp; pretious blood, vouchſafe to blot out all my ſinnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted by auarice, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate loue towards tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral goodes. Which gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy auarice hath made me fall from thy grace, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued me of the participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for as the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayth: <hi>Neither the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous nor extorſioners shall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:150416:143"/> the kingdom of God.</hi> And our Sauiour alſo ſayth in the ghoſpell, <hi>I ſay vnto you it is a hard thing for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of heauen, it is more eaſy for a Camell to goe through the eye of a needel, then for a rich man to enter into heauen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O my bleſſed Redeemer IESVS, the louer of holy pouerty, who haſt through all thy life, from thy firſt entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into this world, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy death, beene a true and perfect obſeruer of this holy precept, giue me thy
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:150416:143"/> grace to be poore in ſpirit, and illuminate my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to know and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne, for the loue of thee, the vilenes, abuſion, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of temporal riches, and of all honour, glorie, pompe &amp; worldly dignity: and to place all my harte, care, and cogitation, in the obtayning of ſpirituall ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, wherby I may poſſeſſe the euerlaſting and eternall treaſures, and to be of the number of them, of whom thou ſpeakeſt in the ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſaying: <hi>Bleſſed are the
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:150416:144"/> poore in ſpirit, for theirs is the kingdome of heauen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <head>THE SIXTHE EF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion on Friday.</head>
                  <p>SIXTHLY, the deuout ſoule ought to thinke, meditate, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template, how our Sauiour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer Iesvs, all the time they were preparing the croſſe, ſett himſelfe vpon the earth, on both his knees, praying to God his Father, that he wold receiue his oblation and ſacrifice, to witt, his moſt ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and bitter death, for
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:150416:144"/> the reconciliation of all poore ſinners, and for the remiſſion of their ſinnes. And how afterwards thoſe inhumane murderers tooke him, and furiouſlie threw him vpon the croſſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he ſpread his ſacred armes of his owne accorde: and how his bleſſed handes and feete, were ſtreightly, and viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlie ſtretched vnto the holes, and hardlie faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with boiſterous nayles, which put him vnto mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous paine, and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable torment.</p>
                  <pb n="284" facs="tcp:150416:145"/>
                  <p>The figure hereof was the Serpent of Bras, which Moyſes cauſed to be made, and ſet it vp for a ſigne, ſo that all thoſe which were ſmitten with any diſeaſe, looking thereon, were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: likewiſe our Lord and Sauiour, being lifted vp and hanging on the croſſe, his pretious blood ranne forth aboundantly on the earth, as if it had beene forthe of foure fountaines, or riuers.</p>
                  <p>Behould here the ſigne eleuated, whereof the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="285" facs="tcp:150416:145"/> foretould ſaying: <hi>Our Lord God shall lift vp a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſigne amonge all nations.</hi> And now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how in all his paines, and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue dolours, as a meeke lambe he is ſilent and ſaieth nothing, vnles it be to pray vnto his bleſſed Father for his enimies, for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, and ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore the deuout ſoule, ought here to reſt him ſelfe, and depeelie to weighe and conſider the exceeding ardour of loue and charitie, which the
<pb n="286" facs="tcp:150416:146"/> bleſſed ſonne of God hath expreſſed and shewed vnto him hanging vpon the Croſſe, and pronouncing thoſe ſeauen ſacred wordes and holie ſentences. And with how great patience, he gaue and reſigned vp his holie life. And how much, and how many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, teares, ſighes, &amp; bitter groanes was then to be heard of his dolorous mother (for then was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the prophecie of holie Simeon, who ſayed that the ſworde of ſorrow
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:150416:146"/> should pierce hir ſoule) &amp; of his other frendes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlding him in ſuch pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful paine, and ſo cruellie faſtned on the croſſe, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced &amp; wounded for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of our ſinnes. And then ought he to ſay with a hart contrit, dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and replenished with compaſſion, and teares of true loue, this deuout pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition following.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The prayer for the ſixt Effuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
                     <p>I Salute the noble blood of my amourous louer, ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:150416:147"/> aboundantlie as foure riuers, out of his pretious body for my redemption, and for the ſatisfaction of my manifold offences. O good IESV, for this maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous charitie, bountie, and mercie which iſſued out of thy bountifull hart, and for that thou waſt ſtretched for vs vpon thy croſſe with ſuch extremitie, and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned theron with ſuch boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous nayles, and for all thy bitter ſorrowes, paines, and dolour, &amp; for the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy ſtripes, iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="289" facs="tcp:150416:147"/> blaſphemies, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guishes, and oppreſſions of thy ſweete and gentle hart, and for all thy afflictions and tribulations which thou pacientlie enduredſt, and principallie in theſe three howers, hanging rufully naked betwixt two Thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, as their head or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: I adore thee, praiſe thee, bleſſe thee, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee humble thankes, praying that thorough thy grace, my olde concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce may be crucified with thee, and that the body of
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:150416:148"/> ſinne, may be mortified and quite diſtroyed in me.</p>
                     <p>O moſt ſweete IESV, I hartelie beſeeche thee, for all the ſtripes, dolours, and paines, of thy bleſſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, &amp; for all the droppes of thy moſt pretious blood, which thou vouchſafedſt to shed, euen to the vtmoſt drop, in ſo much that with thy pretious blood, the Croſſe and the earth were died wholie red: that it would pleaſe thee to take from me, all enuie, detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, obloquie, diſaffection,
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:150416:148"/> hatred, and hard opinion of my neighbour, and to pardon all my offences co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by enuie. For wel I knowe, thou haſt admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed me by thy holie Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaying: <hi>Lay aſide enuies and all detractions.</hi> And Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon ſayeth. <hi>Hatered and enuious haue perished together.</hi> And therefore, my moſt amourous and dearelie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued louer, giue me moſt ardent, perfecte, inuiolable, and perpetuall charitie, and ſo fullie replenish my ſoule there with, that I may firſt
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:150416:149"/> in all thinges perfectly loue thee, and next my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour intirely in thee, and moſt purely and ſincerely for the loue of thee. And that I may from the very bottom of my hart for the loue of thee, pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al thoſe which haue any way offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me, and doe any way hate me: &amp; both to wishe them, and doe them, all kinde of good, to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of myne abilitie; as S. Paule admonisheth ſaying: <hi>If thine enimie hunger, giue him meate: if he thirſt giue hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="293" facs="tcp:150416:149"/> drinke.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O moſt bening IESV, I beſeeche thee by thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable charitie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit mercie, that thou wouldeſt ſo inflame my hart, and wholly ſwallowe it vp in thy loue, that I may neuer be ſeparated from thee. Drawe my hart al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vnto thee, and ſuffer me not to be vanquished by any temptation, nor ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted by any manner of aduerſitie: defend, fortifie, and deliuer me from all ſinne, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the aſſaultes
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:150416:150"/> of mine enimies: gouerne &amp; direct me in all mine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and in all thinges, take vnto thee the totall poſſeſſion of me. Giue me the grace ſo to be inwardly wounded with thy loue, &amp; pittifull paſſion, that in all thinges, and in all places, I may ſtill ſee and behould thee crucifyed for me, that my hart may by loue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually be vnited vnto thee, ſaying with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Dauid: <hi>It is good for me to be vnited &amp; conioyned to my God, and to put my truſt
<pb n="295" facs="tcp:150416:150"/> and confidence in my Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And furthermore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche thee, moſt ſweete IESVS, for all thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt ſuffered thy moſt bitter death and paſſion (to the end that the meritt of the ſame, and of thy excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding charity, may neither be loſt, nor periſh in them) to comfort all thoſe which are in any trouble or affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; to ſupport &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them which are in any temptation: and all thoſe which are in thy holy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, vouchſafe to confirme
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:150416:151"/> them. Conuert againe all ſuch as by imbecillity are fallen, &amp; all ſinners which runne aſtray, and ſaue vs, and glorify vs altogeather, to the end that we may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally laude thee, and perpetually loue thee, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. <hi>Pater noſter, Aue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <head>THE SEAVENTH Effuſion on Saturday.</head>
                  <p>SEauenthlie, vpon the Saturday the deuoute ſoule ought to embrace his meeke Lord louingly with
<pb n="297" facs="tcp:150416:151"/> his hart, and to conſider and contemplate the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and dolorous departure of his ſweet Redeemer and Sauiour IESVS, when his vermillian cheeks &amp; lippes began to waxe pale, his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred eyes to ſend forthgroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and cloddy teares, his holy mouth to be drawen togeather, his reuered head to encline and hang down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and finally his moſt bleſſed ſoule to depart out of his body.</p>
                  <p>The deuoute ſoule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating hereon, ought
<pb n="298" facs="tcp:150416:152"/> to be mollifyed, and with compaſſion to melte, &amp; be quite reſolued into teares, conſidering this ſharpe &amp; bitter death of our bleſſed Lord &amp; Sauiour, &amp; ought alſo to dye with him ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually vnto the world, and to forſake and leaue all ſin, to liue with him eternally.</p>
                  <p>The deuout ſoule ought alſo to thinke, that after his death and paſſion, thoſe wicked &amp; fellonous Iewes, were not yet fully ſatisfyed with thoſe dolours, paines, torments, abuſes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelies,
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:150416:152"/> which already in his life tyme, they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon him: but alſo after his death they adde new torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vnto his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body, &amp; with moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable cruelty, they pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his ſacred ſide, vnto his very hart, whereout iſſued water and blood, as ſayth S. Iohn: <hi>One of the ſouldiers with a ſpeare opened his ſide, and incontinent there iſſued forth blood and water.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thinke, what torment, dolour, anguiſh, ſorrowe, and affliction, this ſtrooke
<pb n="300" facs="tcp:150416:153"/> to the tender hart of his bleſſed mother, who was there preſent. Wherefore to conforme himſelfe to this article, let the deuout ſoule, with great compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, dolour, and compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, hartily ſay this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er following.</p>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>The prayer for the Seauenth Effuſion.</head>
                     <p>I Salute the moſt noble, pretious, and prizeles blood, which iſſued out of the righte ſide of myne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Sauiour IESVS,
<pb n="301" facs="tcp:150416:153"/> hanging dead vpon the Croſſe, by the which blood he hath made full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vnto the diuine Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to recouer and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs from euerlaſting damnation.</p>
                     <p>O my Lord, my God, the hope, &amp; health of al the world, the Creatour of all creatures, who of thy inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible loue, wouldeſt dye a moſt bitter &amp; ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full death, for me a vilde, miſerable, and ſinnefull creature, giue me grace, ſweete IESV I beſeech thee,
<pb n="302" facs="tcp:150416:154"/> that I may dye ſpiritually with thee, and that at the hower of my death, thou receiue my ſoule vnto thy mercy.</p>
                     <p>O moſt ſweet IESV, I recommend my ſoule, and my body into thy handes, extended on the Croſſe, peirced, nayled, and all be-purpled with thy pretious blood. And I aske in all profound humility thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace, that in the laſte hower of my life, I may with good vnderſtanding, and perfect memorie, with
<pb n="303" facs="tcp:150416:154"/> firme fayth, and aſſured hope, reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend my ſoule vnto thy mercy, ſauuegard and ſacred protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And that I may be worthy to heare that ſweet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable voice: <hi>This day thou shalt be with me in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O my amorous Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, who dideſt permit (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou waſt dead) thy bleſſed ſide to be opened with a lance, whereout did iſſue both water &amp; blood: vouchſafe deepely to wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and pierce my ſoule, with
<pb n="304" facs="tcp:150416:155"/> the launce of thy diuine loue: to the end that at the howre of my death, I may be worthy to receiue thy bleſſed body, in the moſt holy and bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as a ſpirituall foode againſt the euerlaſting famine, &amp; thy pretious blood, for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable drinke, againſt the eternall and vnquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable thirſt.</p>
                     <p>In the opening of thy ſacred ſide, O my gratious Lord, thou haſt opened to thyne elect, the gate of Paradice, and of eternall
<pb n="305" facs="tcp:150416:155"/> life. I beſeech thee deare IESV, haue not memory of my ſinnes &amp; iniquities, leaſt this gate and entry be ſhut and cloſed againſt me for myne offences, which thou haſt mercifully ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to all poore ſinners, penitents and repentants: but receaue my ſoule at the hower of my death fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably vnto thy mercy, and place it with thee in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ioy and felicity.</p>
                     <p>And furthermore ſweet IESV I beſeeche thee, for the honor of al thy paines,
<pb n="306" facs="tcp:150416:156"/> dolours, death, and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and for the Effuſion of thy moſt pretious blood: that thou wouldeſt pardon me all my grieuous ſinnes of carnality, committed in thoughts, wordes, deedes, or motions, by my diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affection of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, and ſenſuall dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation. And that I may follow and performe the councell of S. Paul ſaying: <hi>Mortify your ſinnefull mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi> And againe: <hi>If you liue according to the flesh you shall dye, but if by the ſpirit
<pb n="307" facs="tcp:150416:156"/> you ſubdue the workes of the flesh, you shall liue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Giue me, deare IESV, I beſeeche thee, this faire An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall vertue of Chaſtity, of Continence, Purity of ſoule, and body. Sweet IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SV, mortify and kill in me all vices, all motions, and prouocations to concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and carnal affection. Take from me I beſeeche thee, all that which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, diſordinate, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to thy diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty: and giue me a harte moſt ſimple, cleane pure,
<pb n="308" facs="tcp:150416:157"/> feruent, diuine, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to thy owne hart, which no vicious, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate affection, may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer infect, ſoile or macu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</p>
                     <p>My Lord, my God, &amp; moſt compaſſionate ſpouſe of my ſoule, I beſeech thee, to keep &amp; defend me from all wicked, vnlawfull, and vicious deedes: from all vnſeemely, vncleane, and hurtfull take, and from all euill, fleſhly, and filthie thoughtes, that I may wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely and faythfully ſerue
<pb n="309" facs="tcp:150416:157"/> thee, in all pureneſſe of ſoule and body.</p>
                     <p>Sweet IESV, take the whole poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my hart vnto thee, and giue me ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyne owne harte, or make this hart of myne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable vnto thyn, to the end that all my thoughtes, willes, and deſires, may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be in thee, &amp; to thy honour and glory, and that I may perpetually repoſe in thee, ſaying with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: <hi>My ſoule shall reſt and ſleepe in peace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Finally, moſt mercifull
<pb n="309" facs="tcp:150416:158"/> IESV, I pray thee for the ſoules of my pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and benefactors, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie for al the ſoules, in the fire of Purgatorie; humblie beſeeching thee, by thy cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, goodnes, and infinite bountie, &amp; by the merit of thy moſt holie death and paſſion, to deliuer and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe them of their paines &amp; torments, and to giue them perpetuall &amp; euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting reſt. Amen. <hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Aue Maria. Credo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div xml:lang="fre" type="license">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150416:158"/>
                  <head>PREVILEGE.</head>
                  <p>PHilippe par la grace de Dieu Roy de Caſtile, d'Arragon, &amp;c. permet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons de grace eſpecialle à IEAN HEIGHAM d'Imprimer, ou faire im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primer les ſix liures Spirituelles en An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glois, à l'excluſion de tous autres, pour l'eſpace de quinze ans, commençant le 1. de Iullet 1622. à peine de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiſcation &amp; amende mentioné en ledit Prouilege.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signé</hi> LE COMTE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
